<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anna Trapnel's report and plea, or, A narrative of her journey into Cornwal the occasion of it, the Lord's encouragements to it, and signal presence with her in it, proclaiming the rage and strivings of the people against the comings forth of the Lord Jesus to reign ... whereto is annexed a defiance against all the reproachful, vile, horrid ... reports raised out of the bottomless pit against her ... / commended for the justification of the truth, and satisfaction of all men, from her own hand.</title>
            <author>Trapnel, Anna.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2033</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32888</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12777149</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12777149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93777</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63061)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93777)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1537:53)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anna Trapnel's report and plea, or, A narrative of her journey into Cornwal the occasion of it, the Lord's encouragements to it, and signal presence with her in it, proclaiming the rage and strivings of the people against the comings forth of the Lord Jesus to reign ... whereto is annexed a defiance against all the reproachful, vile, horrid ... reports raised out of the bottomless pit against her ... / commended for the justification of the truth, and satisfaction of all men, from her own hand.</title>
                  <author>Trapnel, Anna.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at London for Thomas Brewster ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata sheet bound at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Witness bearing (Christianity)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93777:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93777:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ANNA TRAPNEL</hi>'s Report and Plea. OR, A NARRATIVE Of her Journey from <hi>London</hi> into <hi>Cornwal,</hi> the occaſion of it, the Lord's encouragements to it, and ſignal preſence with her in it. Proclaiming the rage and ſtrivings of the People a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the comings forth of the Lord Jeſus to reign; manifeſted, in the harſh, rough, boiſterous, rugged, inhumane, and uncivil uſage of <hi>Anna Trapnel,</hi> by the Juſtices and people in <hi>Cornwal,</hi> at a place called <hi>Truro.</hi> Whereto is annexed A DEFIANCE Againſt all the reproachful, vile, horrid, abuſive, and ſcandalous reports, raiſed out of the bottomleſs pit againſt her, by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane generation, prompted thereunto by Profeſſors and Clergie both in Citie and Country, <hi>who have a form of godlineſs, but deny the power.</hi> Commended for the juſtification of the Truth, and ſatisfaction of all men, from her own hand.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>Thomas Brewſter,</hi> at the three Bibles, neer <hi>London</hi>-houſe. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:93777:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93777:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord, and my Father (Courteous Reader) having put me upon this work and imployment, I pray don't call it i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſs, leſt you would be likened to thoſe <hi>who call good evil, and evil good; and put darkneſs for light, and light for dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> againſt whom there is a woe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced from the Lord<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 5.20.</note>: and is it not dreadful to come under the woe of the Lord? ſure it is much better to come under mens threats, ſcourges, and contempt; and when for well-doing too, what <hi>ſhall harm you if you be follower of that which is good</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13.</note>? whatſoever is done to the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in heart, it's no harm: <hi>If ye ſuffer for righteouſneſs ſake, happy are ye; and be not afraid of their terrour, nor be troubled.</hi> I bleſs the Lord, my ſufferings are for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſake, and I go not about to vindicate my ſelf, but Truth; which indeed ſtands in no need of mine or any ones vindication; but I would ſhew love and reſpect to it, in oppoſition to thoſe, who with ſpades
<pb facs="tcp:93777:3"/>and ſhovels dig up mire and rubbiſh to throw upon it. Power and Spear is drawn againſt the Lord and his Anointed; for the holy Unction that the holy One hath given his, they ſuffer, and who can be ſad? what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is laid upon them by men or devils, when thereby they are not loſers, but great gainers from the Lord, though loſers from men: and therefore men may give loſers leave to ſpeak to them, which have offered them ſo much injurie. But the Lord knows, I would not reach out tongue, hand nor pen, to right my ſelf, or to ſeek reſtauration of my loſs, I wave that, ſuch a thing is below my ſpirit. I bleſs the Lord, &amp; truly I do not herein boaſt, neither would I glory in any thing, ſave in my infirmities; not in my ſins, but in reproaches, and vilifyings, which the Apoſtle ſaith, He will glory in:<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30.</note> 
               <hi>I will,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>glory of the things which concern mine infirmities.</hi> He could glory in the Lords fatherly ſtrokes, as looking unto all things to work for the good of his ſoul, ſeeing his Fathers love in all that was done unto him, giving him a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand-fold for his outward damage. And though I am a poor inferiour, unworthy to be compared with any of the holy men or women reported of in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; yet I can ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> Through grace I am what I am; and I live, yet not I, but Chriſt lives in me; and the life that I live, is by the faith of the Son of God, who died and gave himſelf for a weak hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, as well as for a ſtrong <hi>Paul.</hi> And my deſire is to imitate that approved <hi>Hannah</hi> in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. who was in bitterneſs of ſoul, and prayed unto the Lord, and wept ſore for a <hi>Samuel,</hi> wherein God might be glorified and advanced in and by that typical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, who held forth Chriſt that great Prophet, that
<pb facs="tcp:93777:3"/>lives for ever, who maketh fruitful, and removes barrenneſs. And if hand-maids in theſe dayes pray and weep for their Lord, begging his coming to rule in them, and in the Nation, and to teach all ſorts of people his ſtatutes, that ſo the ſtatutes of <hi>Omri</hi> might be utterly ruinated, ſuch praying cannot be borne by the Inhabitants of this Nation; there is ſuch an old evil ſpirit of miſ-conſtruing, and judging holy actions to carry in them evil conſequences. <hi>Eli</hi> the Prieſt of the Lord, is imitated in his worſt part. <hi>England</hi>'s Rulers and Clergie do judge the Lords hand-maid to be mad, and under the adminiſtration of evil angels, and a witch, and many other evil terms they raiſe up to make me odious, and abhorr'd in the hearts of good and bad, that do not know me.</p>
            <p>Pray, Chriſtian Reader, well obſerve the enſuing Diſcourſe, whereby you may underſtand the voice of malice and envie uttered and acted by the Clergie and Rulers againſt me, who hath ſhewed much love and friendſhip to them for many yeers, and yet is no Enemy to her Enemies; but prayeth for them. I am ſure they have ſinned far more then old <hi>Eli,</hi> who ſaid of <hi>Hannah,</hi> She was Drunk. This grieved her, and made her reply and ſay, <hi>Don't count thy hand-maid for a daughter of Belial, for out of the abundance of my complaint and grief have I ſpoken hitherto. Then Eli ſaid, Go in peace, and the God of Iſrael grant thy petition that thou haſt asked of him.</hi> Here is a recantation quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſted; and it's probable, he was exceedingly troubled, for afflicting the afflicted. What raſh Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers imitate him in this part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> though he was the chief-Prieſt in his dayes, yet he thought it no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement to talk with a poor hand-maid, being a
<pb facs="tcp:93777:4"/>ſober holy woman. Therefore I inſtance this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, Reader, that thou maiſt take notice how far ſhort the great Rabbies come of Scripture-Rule in theſe dayes of the Goſpel, wherein they ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, not in pride, haughtineſs and lofty carriages; but in humility, and in acknowledging the wrong and evil judgement that they have brought forth, and paſſed upon the innocent. And as to what they have ſaid, and paſſed ſentence, may not <hi>Judas</hi> riſe up in the Judgement-day of the Lord, and condemn theſe men, who acknowledged his evil? and likewiſe <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> who confeſſed his ſin, and deſired prayer; and many Heathens did ſo, recorded in Scripture, and in many Hiſtories beſides, which the learned are not ignorant of? and ſhall Heathens, and a vile <hi>Iudas,</hi> a Spirit-abuſing <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> condemn thoſe that are accounted Chriſtians, great in wiſdom and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and eloquent ſpeeches, and full of guilded words, brave Orators, great head-pieces, ſo called; but is it not more commendable to be in heart, then in head? <hi>My ſon, give me thy heart.</hi> And the Lord ſaith, when Iſrael did ſo word it with him, <hi>Oh that there were ſuch an heart:</hi> Here is brave language, fair promiſes; but, <hi>Oh that there were ſuch an heart!</hi> Deut. 5.28. an heart comparable with ſuch words, God loves, which brings ſayings out into doings; he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in golden actions, not in guilded words; he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteems reality, not falſhood. Who can forbear taking up a Lamentation concerning poor <hi>ENGLAND:</hi> whoſe Prophets propheſie falſly, and the Prieſts bear Rule by their means, and the people love to have it ſo; but what will they do in the end thereof? for ſure the end will be ſad, when the Lord ſhall come
<pb facs="tcp:93777:4"/>out as a ſwift Witneſs againſt the Seers of <hi>ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND,</hi> for ſtrengthening <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Popes Dominion, and dreſſing the Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Whore in new clothes, ſo as to blinde and decieve Cities and Countries, telling them, That it's the true genuine fruit of the Womb of the Church, and Spouſe of CHRIST, when it will indeed be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to be from the Harlots brood, and ſo a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard, which is ſentenced by the LORD according to Scripture, ſurely to die, and the day of the LORD's vengeance will ſlay it; for the LORD hath pronounced deſtruction to <hi>Babylons</hi> Brats, as well as to <hi>Babylon:</hi> why then ſhould contention be for the Whores Brats?</p>
            <p>Reader, I beſeech this of thee, whoſoever thou beeſt; under Forms, or without forms; obedient to Ordinances for the LORD's ſake, or yet in the dark concerning them: I beſeech all ſorts of people, high and low, to weigh in the balance of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, the true Relation which followeth; for I ſhall relate the Truth without addition: though I cannot (it may be) remember all the paſſages in order, yet as many as the LORD brings to my minde, I ſhall relate, for the ſatisfaction of the LORD's friends known and unknown in all parts where the rumour hath run.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93777:5"/>
            <p>A Declaration from my own hand ſhall follow, not being put on by any, ſave by the great Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, who counſelleth with his eye, who beareth me out before men and devils. The LORD is on my ſide, I will not fear men, what they can do; the LORD is my help and refuge. Farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſervant that loves Chriſt in ſincerity, <hi>A.T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93777:5"/>
            <head>Here begins the NARRATIVE or RELATION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, I ſhall give an account of my Invitation from friends, which ſaid, <hi>Pray go down with us to Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wal; there you may do good to poor ſouls, with the variety of Experiences God hath given you.</hi> But I ſaid, <hi>There's a far journey indeed! Do you think I would leave all my friends, to go ſo far from them? they would take it very ill, ſurely.</hi> They ſaid to me, <hi>We have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited you; we pray you ſpread it before the Lord, and hearken to his minde in it; and we will pray and wait for the Lords anſwer.</hi> I ſaid, I would pray againſt going to <hi>Cornwal:</hi> if I ſhould finde any inclination or motion to go, I would not hearken to it, my minde was ſo ſtrongly bent againſt that journey. But two days after, in the night, I was praying to the Lord in my bed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly; and I deſired I might abide neer my <hi>London</hi>-friends, that ſo I might enjoy ſociety with them that I was in Church-order with, who were ſo dear to me, and were written in my heart. But the Lord that night perſwaded my heart to pray to him for his preſence in the journey to <hi>Cornwal,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Do n't pray agairst it any more: for there thou muſt go.</hi> And much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion was given in to my heart, by the ſecret whiſperings of the Spirit. And the Scripture-ſayings I had that night, were theſe: The firſt was <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.9. <hi>The Lord thy God is with thee whitherſoever thou goest.</hi> And again, I had that ſaying, <hi>Where canſt thou flee from my preſence, or where canst thou go from my Spirit?</hi> Pſal. 139.7. I then ſaid, <hi>Truth, Lord, whither can I go from thy Spirit, or flee from thy preſence? Then do n't fear to go to Corur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wal, though it be a long journey,</hi> ſaid the Lord, <hi>for I will go with thee:</hi> then I ſaid, <hi>Lord, let me have thy Spirit and preſence in places
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93777:6"/>neer London; why ſhould I go ſo far, and among ſtrangers?</hi> the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was, <hi>Fear not, be not diſcouraged: thy God, who is thy Father, goeth with thee:</hi> then I mourned before the Lord, and ſaid, <hi>I pray Father let me not go:</hi> then the Lord ſaid, <hi>Thou reaſoneſt as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes did when he was to go to Pharoah: he cavilled againſt the minde of God, and ſo do'ſt thou:</hi> then that ſaying was given into my heart, <hi>The Lord hath purpoſed thy going there, and his purpoſe and counſel ſhallſtand, and he will do his pleaſure; it pleaſeth him, thy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there:</hi> and then I had that Scripture in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.10. <hi>Fear thou not, for I am with thee: be not diſmayed, for I am thy God: I will ſtrengthen thee, yea, I will help thee, yea, I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteouſneſs; therefore,</hi> ſaid the Lord, <hi>be willing to go:</hi> and then my reaſoning gainſaying ſpirit fell flat before the Lord, and I prayed, <hi>Thy will, O Lord, be done; thy word coming with ſuch power and great authority on my heart, I can no longer contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict it:</hi> then I had this ſaying, <hi>Out of the mouth of two or three witneſſes things are confirmed. I have,</hi> ſaid the Lord, <hi>given thee many confirming Scriptures for thy establiſhment concerning thy journey: therefore be ſtrong in thy Fathers ſtrength; rely upon him that will not forſake thee, nor leave thee; but will be thy guide unto death.</hi> Then I told my ſiſter, <hi>I thought I muſt go to Cornwal;</hi> the which ſhe liked not; but contradicted. And the day after this nights debating and arguing, I told ſome of the Church I walk with, <hi>That I was perſwaded to go to Cornwal:</hi> they were much againſt it, and ſaid to me, <hi>You will not we hope do ſo, we are againſt your leaving us to go ſo far; and will you leave us in ſuch a time as this?</hi> Many of my ſiſters were troubled at my firſt ſpeaking of going; but when I had related the Scriptures I had for my going, then they were ſilent for that time; and I told them, <hi>That if I had not a further call from God to the journey, I would not go; it being ſuch an extraordinary journey, I would not go without an extraordinary call further from the Lord, ſealing me up thereunto.</hi> And going down to <hi>Hillington</hi> neer <hi>Uxbridge,</hi> by the way, as I rode, I ſtill was filled with apprehenſions of my journey into <hi>Cornwal,</hi> the joy I ſhould have by the way, and what benefit others would have through a poor creature. And when I came to my friends houſe at <hi>Hillington,</hi> I lay all next day ſilent, but exceedingly filled with the preſence of the Lord, who ſhewed me a viſion of my <hi>Cornwal</hi>-journey: I
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93777:6"/>beheld high rocky-hills, and variety of places and towns, and how I ſhould be as I rode in the Coach, much melody I ſhould have; this I ſaw, and heard this ſaying, <hi>That as ſure as Paul in</hi> Act. 16.9. <hi>had a viſion appeared in the night: There ſtood a man of Macedonia and prayed Paul, ſaying, Come over into Macedonia and help us;</hi> &amp; the Lord ſaid, <hi>as truely do I thy Lord call thee to Cornwal by this viſion:</hi> then I anſwered, and ſaid, <hi>Paul was to preach there, what is that word to me?</hi> then reply was, <hi>But as ſure as his was a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the Lord to go to Macedonia, ſo as ſure had I a call and true viſion to go to Cornwal:</hi> then ſinging triumph was given me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the journey thither, how filled I ſhould be by the way: which was ſo. And then after I had thus ſang and prayed, I rode to ſee the Lords two Embaſſadours which were impriſoned in <hi>Windſor</hi>-Caſtle for the teſtimony of Jeſus, Mr. <hi>Simpſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Feak,</hi> who were filled with the Spirit abundantly: and when I a while beheld their courage for King Jeſus, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, with other friends, back to my friends houſe at <hi>Hilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and the next day rode to a friends houſe ſix miles off, where I abode two nights. And as I was walking in the fields, I was ſuddenly very hoarſe, and I could not well ſpeak, but ſoftly: and I was greatly tempted as I walked in the fields, that I ſhould be hoarſe while I lived, like as a woman of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation was, with whom I walk; ſo ſhould I be, not able to ſpeak but hoarſly, <hi>And therefore go not thy journey,</hi> ſaid Satan, <hi>for that extraordinary diſpenſation of prayer and ſinging ſhall not be with thee; then they will not regard thee whom thou goeſt with, for they look at that, and not at thee; and that departing from thee, thou wilt not be regarded by them; and being in a ſtrange place, how ſad then will it be with thee? and they are but ſtrangers to thee; Acquaintance with them hath been but a little while: therefore don't go.</hi> Thus Satan and my fearful nature joyned together to fruſtrate what I had ſpoken from the Lord concerning my going, being ſealed up for the journey; &amp; always after ſealing unto any work of the Lord, Satan tempts me; but ſuch is the goodneſs of the Lord to me, who lets not out Satan till he hath firſt eſtabliſhed me; and then before I have the mercy, the ſentence of death is put upon what is in order to the bringing it forth to view: ſo that the Lord thereby ſtrengthens me the more, and makes me live by faith, which is the life of the juſt: it's a lovely life
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93777:7"/>the life of faith. But further, as for Satans temptations, they laſted but for half a day, and a little part of the night, and they were removed; for in the night in my ſleep the Lord refreſhed me with many Scriptures, as being my refuge, ſtay, and defence, and ſtrong Tower, guide and ſuccourer. And at break of day I awoke out of ſleep, refreſhed as one with new wine; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I had that night ſuch well-refined wine, as Scripture makes mention of. And hearing the birds cherup in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning early, about my chamber-window; I had this ſaying given into my heart, <hi>Thou heareſt thoſe birds in their notes and motion, which pleaſeth thy ear: And doth the great Creator take care of birds, ſtill maintaining them with a ſupply of food ſuitable for them, that ſo they may live, and be lively in their ſervice to man? And doth God take care of fowls, that not a ſparrow ſhall fall to the ground without the Fathers providence or ordering it to be ſo? then what care and proviſion doth he make for rational created pieces, which the whole Trinity was in the make thereof: as for other pieces,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>Let it be, and it was ſo; but as to mans make, the whole Trinity gave their judgement. And,</hi> ſaid the Lord to me, <hi>hath God honoured thee with this firſt honour, in making thee a rational peice, and alſo giving thee a ſhare and intereſt in the death and reſurrection of his Son, and hath made thee partaker of the divine nature, of that heavenly-born ſtate, of that ſecond creation in Chriſt, ſpoken of in</hi> Eph. 2.19. <hi>Art thou thus provided for, to be made a poſſeſſor of two cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation-works, a firſt and a ſecond? and alſo haſt thou the Spirit of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption whereby thou canſt cry, Abba, Father? then having done thus much for thee, will he withhold any thing that's good for thee? he will not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I felt my hoarſneſs removed from me preſently, and all my temptations which I told you the day before did ſo ſeize upon my Spirits: and the Lord renewed my faith concerning my journey, and made me to rejoyce over Satan. And I aroſe, and rode that day to meet with ſome of the Lords ſervants, where a day of thankſgiving was kept, for many ſpecial favours received from the Lord, and for his upholding comforting preſence in ſufferings; and there I ſtayed till night: in which day I beheld much of divine preſence and glory coming towards the Saints, and great ruine unto the enemies, which were preſented to me
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93777:7"/>like a tottering houſe, that ſtands ſhaking and ready to fall. And I had that ſaying, <hi>So doth and ſhall totter all the towers and Babels builded and rear'd up in contempt to King Jeſus, who will confound all ſuch builders and their work,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>They that build hay, or wood, or gold, or ſilver, or any thing of their own materials, it ſhall be burnt,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. <hi>this foundation will admit of nothing of mans corruptible ſtuff to be joyned with it; for it is compleat, and will compleat his ſervants that build upon him.</hi> Then when this thankſgiving-day was ended, I rode to my friends houſe at <hi>Hillington,</hi> where I was filled with joy and ſinging moſt part of that night; and the next day I rode to another friends, where I ſtayed; the next day, being the firſt day of the week, that day I went to hear a Miniſter which preacht a mile off, in whoſe miniſtery the Spirit much warmed my heart, and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Spirits; and though I was ill in my outward man all that day, yet the matter I heard was ſo reviving, being ſpiritual, that at night thinking of it, and walking in a curious garden, where I ſaw the pleaſant trees, and plants, and walks, and fiſh-ponds, and hearing the birds pleaſant notes, all this begat ſuch an harmonious apprehenſion of God in my heart, that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſing forth his praiſes, and continued while it was ſo late in the evening, that my friends that walked with me thought it convenient to lead me into the houſe; which they can beſt give an account of; for I minded not the time, nor thoſe that were with me, neither can I tell whether I felt the ground I walkt upon; my Spirits was ſo much in divine rapture, and my Spirits ſo heat with Spirit-fire, which produced ſinging-melody while midnight, the which ſinging ſpeech was directed to the whole family, and thoſe belonging to it at that time; which family conſiſted of many perſons, grave, and judicious, and learned, underſtanding perſons, before whom I thought my ſelf unfit to ſpeak, when I was in an ordinary capacity; but being filled extraordinarily, I wanted not words compoſed and orderly, and learning for the learned. Herein I don't boaſt, but in the rich free love of God, who gives to whom he pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Then after that ſinging, I was put to bed, being weak in body and head, between two friends, where I lay and prayed till the morning; and coming into my ordinary capacity, I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93777:8"/>roſe and had ſtrength of body: though I could not eat the day before, nor after this night thus ſpeaking ſo much; yet I was not dry, neither could I take any creature-refreſhing, though I had much offered me. This I mention, to advance Chriſt, and not for any by-end. Then my friends ſent me in their Coach to <hi>London,</hi> where I prepared for my <hi>Cornwal</hi>-journey all that week.</p>
            <p>Coming to my habitation the ſecond day of the week, that week I had much of the Lord's preſence in marvelous joy, and yet many temptations between whiles; the tempter tempted me againſt my journey: and when I went up a pair of ſtairs, I was tempted that I ſhould fall from the top to the bottom of the ſtairs and break my limbes, ſo that I ſhould in ſuch a way be hindered my journey; and I was often tempted that week before I went, that ſome evil ſhould befal me, to hinder me from going to <hi>Cornwal;</hi> or ſome would hear of my going, that would ſtop it. And then Satan ſaid, <hi>What will become of all thy faith, and the ſinging report concerning it?</hi> And ſometimes I was thus hurried, yet I ſtaggered not in my faith concerning the truth of what I had mentioned about my journey, that it ſhould ſurely be as I had believed; and I waited for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of it. And the ſixth day of that week I took my leave of my Tower-friends, ſitting up till the morning with them, all the night praying and praiſing with them with joy, more then an ordinary capacity could hold. And in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I went to bed, and lay ſome hours, and then roſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode there that day and night: and the next day, being the firſt day of this following week, I bid my Tower-friends <hi>farewel;</hi> and ſo departed from them, taking my leave alſo of other friends by the way as I went to <hi>Alhallows,</hi> where I met with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation that I am in fellowſhip with, which uſe to break bread there. And I that day ſaw great ſhinings, and taſted much of my Saviour that day, who preſenting his love lineſs in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, and his ſweetneſs in the ſupper of breaking bread, which filled my heart with joy unſpeakable and glorious in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving. And then after the Ordinances were ended, I took my leave of many friends there, who gave me their exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with counſel and prayer for my well-doing; and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from them, begging their prayers for me when abſent in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93777:8"/>the body: and half a ſcore of my ſiſters kept that night in prayer with me at my friends houſe from whence I was to take my journey the next day. And having thus ſpent the night in ſweet communion with God, I was prepared for my journey: I wanted not ſleep nor food-preparation, having had the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial revivement liquors from my Lord Jeſus, which ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me for my travelling to <hi>Cornwal.</hi> And I ſaid to my friends, <hi>I pray be much in ſpiritual communion together, and don't forget to mention before the Lord your unworthy ſiſter at a diſtance.</hi> Thus deſiring their remembrance of me, they departed from me; and I and my friends for the journey, went by water from Southwark to White-Hall-ſtairs, where we landed, and went to the Inne where we took Coach; and many friends came to bid us <hi>farewel,</hi> &amp; among them came one who ſaid to ſome after I was gone, That <hi>if he had known me, and had known I was going into his country, he would have procured the Councels Order to have ſtopt my journey, for the love he bore to his country; which ſure he thought I would corrupt, and make like my ſelf:</hi> which he thought to have hindered; but the Lord prevented his deſire: for my Father would have me go there, and Satan nor men could not hinder me.</p>
            <p>So we rode on our journey toward the Weſt: and in the firſt dayes journey, my thoughts were taken up with the work of the praying Saints, which met that day at <hi>Alhallows,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſecond day, which they uſe to keep for the Reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kingdom of Iſrael, praying and ſpeaking for that concernment which is ſo glorious; and my thoughts were very ſeriouſly intent upon generation-work, praying with them at <hi>Alhallows</hi> in the Spirit, though I was abſent from them in body: and meeting with a dear friend by the way, who told me he intended to go to <hi>Alhallow,</hi> meeting that day; I ſaid, <hi>I pray remember what was earnestly deſired of you, that you would aſſiſt the Church in the wilderneſs, and be helpful in the ſecond dayes meeting, keeping cloſe to the work of the preſent day: and I deſired his prayer for me in my abſence;</hi> more words paſſed between us as he rode by the Coach-ſide a little way: then he bid farewel, and departed; and my joy was encreaſed at the ſight of that precious ſervant of Chriſt, whoſe words left a fragranſie upon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93777:9"/>my Spirits ſome part of the day; and the enjoyment of prayer in the Spirit with them at <hi>Alhallows,</hi> took up the other part of the day; onely ſpeaking a little ſometimes to my friends, with whom I went. At night we came to our Inne, where I had much refreſhings in a little medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods goodneſs to me that day: and after prayer I went to my bed, and was refreſhed with ſights of the Lord in my ſleep; and roſe in the morning, taking another dayes journey: and in much diſcourſe we ſpent that ſecond dayes journey. And I rode the next day with the ſame perſons as I did the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and my Spirit then was all that day in a praying and ſinging frame, and ſo it remained till night; and then we came to <hi>Salisbury,</hi> where we parted with the Judge that rode in the Coach with us; for there the Judges met in their Circuit: and there I was mightily fill'd with apprehenſions of Chriſt's Circuit he was taking in the earth, and of that bleſſed time that the Saints ſhould judge the earth, when in that time the earth ſhould not paſs their falſe judgements on the Saints: and moſt part of that night I was thus: and they that were with me, ſaw and felt on my outward man, which was like a dead clod, I was ſo cold a great while. And the fourth daies journey I ſang &amp; prayed almoſt the whole day: and ſo I did the fifth daies journey, ſinging much of the creation-excellencies, as trees, graſs, and ſeveral plants, and corn that grew as I went by. And though I rode through townes, I minded not any ſpeakings of creatures; for indeed I was not capable of outward ſayings or doings, nor of the ratling of the Coach thoſe two dayes. And the laſt day of that week we came to <hi>Exceter;</hi> which day I was very cheerful in the Lord, though not ſo very much as the dayes before: there we inned at an old diſciples houſe, a widow, one Mrs. <hi>Winter</hi>'s, a houſe that many yeers had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained and lodged Saints, which in their travelling ſtill took up their quarters there: and I lay there three nights: and the day after, being the firſt day of another week, I went to hear the Word preached at the Caſtle in <hi>Exceter,</hi> where I kept this firſt day with the Church that met there; and there I ſaw my <hi>London</hi>-friends, that a while had dwelt in the Caſtle: and I continued till late in the evening with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93777:9"/>them, relating the goodneſs of the Lord to me by the way of my journey, and acquainting them with the welfare of <hi>London</hi>-friends; and how joyfully the priſoners at Windſor-Caſtle took their ſufferings, it being upon ſo noble an account. And theſe friends wondred much at my taking ſo long a journey, and ſaid, <hi>Sure ſome extraordinary thing was to be made manifeſt in my going ſo far; and therefore they would hearken after it, and obſerve the Lords work in it:</hi> for they thought there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then ordinary to be brought forth, in that I was carried ſo far a journey, and having ſo little acquaintance with them I went with: which made them admire what the Lord would do with me; and ſo did many: and my ſelf alſo thought and was perſwaded, That the Lord would ſhew ſome ſpecial favours to me, and ſo he did; I largely thereof enjoyed before my return back again: and I took leave of thoſe friends that night, and came to my lodging at Mrs. <hi>Winters.</hi> The next day the Lord greatly raviſhed my ſoul with his ſmiling looks on me, and he filled me that day with prayer, and ſinging, and diſcovering the tottering, ſhaking condition of Clergie-Function. And likewiſe praying for many particular friends at <hi>London;</hi> and ſpecially for them at <hi>Alhallows</hi>-meeting, and for thoſe friends at the Caſtle forementioned, ſpeaking to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of their conditions; and likewiſe begging ſinners to come to Chriſt. And I ſpake to variety of conditions that day, wherein many ſouls were refreſhed. And I lay all that night in a rapture of great joy, and had ſights of my further journey, how God would carry me ſafe, and with much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs to my journies end; the which we went towards in the morning, it being the third day of the week; in which day we parted with Colonel <hi>Bennet,</hi> and his Daughter, and Servants; and his Wife bore me company, with Captain <hi>Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and his Wife, and their Servants; this was our company that went from <hi>Exceter</hi> together, and lodged by the way that night: which dayes journey was very ſweet to us; and we had much of the Lord's preſervation with us. Then the next day, which was the fourth day, we came to Colonel <hi>Bennet</hi>'s houſe, where we lodged that night; and my heart was very chearfully carried on in reading over every dayes mercy, when I came to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93777:10"/>my lodging. And the next day after dinner, we took our leave there, and parted with Colonel <hi>Bennet</hi>'s Wife at her houſe, who ſhewed me much love, and told me, <hi>She would ſend for me to her houſe again, after a little time expired.</hi> Col. <hi>Bennet,</hi> by the way as we journeyed, being taken much with my experiences, ſaid, <hi>They were not to be hid, but they were to be manifeſted for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of others;</hi> &amp; ſaid, <hi>He would have me ride to ſome of his friends houſes: for that diſpenſation of the Lord on me, was not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed.</hi> And indeed he manifeſted much kindneſs to me as we journeyed in company together, and charged his daughter to be very tenderly careful of me; for that I was not in a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to minde my outward man. This his kindneſs laſted to <hi>Exceter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now to come again to my journeying from his houſe in <hi>Cornwal,</hi> which I told you we departed from after dinner, and came to Captain <hi>Langdons</hi> ſiſter, where we lodged, and were lovingly entertained the fifth day; and there I had much love from God, and from ſtrangers, and a very refreſhing lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the creatures were very ſweet to my taſte there. As for the ſix dayes before we came to <hi>Exceter,</hi> I eat very little: but we went from thence, the ſixth day: after breakfaſt, we took our leave of thoſe Relations of Captain <hi>Langdons.</hi> And the ſixth day at night, we came to Mrs. <hi>Langdons</hi> brothers houſe, where we received a courteous entertainment, and a refreſhing lodge; and my heart there was taken up much with the apprehenſion of the vanity of outward enjoyments, and great attendances, and brave houſes: and my thoughts were much upon the Rocks I paſſed by in my journey, &amp; the dangerous rocky places I rode over. And whereas I uſed to be very fearful, when I rode on ſmooth ground, now I feared not, but was very cheerfully car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on, beholding my Rock, Chriſt, through thoſe emblems of Rocks: and I ſate as in a chair upon the high ſteep hills, without any weariſomneſs at all; and the thoughts of the Lords kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to me in theſe things, drunk up my thoughts that night: and the next day we came ſafe to our journeys end, at <hi>Trega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſow,</hi> at Captain <hi>Langdons</hi> habitation, and there we ended our journey the laſt day of the week, which had been accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thirteen dayes. And the Lord much appeared to all of us
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93777:10"/>the whole journey; praiſed he his Name, whoſe Name was to us indeed a ſtrong Tower. The Lord was our munition of Rocks, and large proviſion every way to ſouls and bodies. And thus I have given an account as briefly as I could of my journey-progreſs, and bleſſed fare by the way, and of the extraordinary and ordinary breakings forth of the light of his countenance and communications, all along thoſe thirteen dayes now expired.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here follows a Relation, in the next place, of ſeveral paſſages and actings by creatures, in a way of love and hatred, ſome frowning, few ſmiling; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rejecting, few receiving: manifeſted from the firſt day, to the laſt day of my abode there in <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wal,</hi> in the Weſt. Alſo, of my impriſonment in Bridewel, and my enlargment therefrom.</head>
               <p>I Shall now begin the Relation of my firſt coming to Captain <hi>Langdons</hi> houſe, where there came many of Captain <hi>Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons</hi> acquaintance, to ſee them at their firſt coming home; and moſt of them gave me but a ſowre greeting, they having been informed before concerning my Spirit, as it was reported to me afterwards; but they frowningly and diſſemblingly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted me, though their hearts were againſt me, as many of them made it to appear largely afterwards; and ſome became loving friends among them, that loved me not when I firſt came; but I ſeeing theſe unlovely carriages from the moſt part of them that came there that evening and afternoon, it made me very thoughtful what it would produce. I ſate down in the room a while, where I heard many diſcourſes from them to one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and with Captain <hi>Langdon;</hi> and I not reliſhing the diſcourſe, had a minde to walk in the Garden by my ſelf, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93777:11"/>ſo I did a while; wherein the Lord gave me much of his loving-welcome, and kinde ſalutations, ſaying, <hi>Though thou ſeest many frown on thee, it ſhall not make thee ſad; for thy Saviour will ſmile on thy ſoul in all conditions:</hi> and that ſaying made my heart revive preſently; and then the Lord gave me that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-ſaying, <hi>This he requires of thee, To deal justly, love mercy, and walk humbly with thy God,</hi> Micah 6.8. then I ſaid, <hi>Lord, what am I to do here?</hi> The Lord ſaid, <hi>I require this, that thou holdeſt out a juſt, upright walk with God before all people; and in theſe parts thou ſhalt manifest the free juſtification received of the Father by the Spirit through Chriſt to poor ſouls; telling them thy experiences there: and thou ſhalt declare the mercy of thy God, and thy love to it, by ſhewing thy experiences thereof, which thou hast had in divers maners diſcovered to thee. Here are ſome tempted ſouls,</hi> ſaid the Lord, <hi>that muſt be comforted through thy temptations; the mercy thou foundſt therein, tell them: love mercy in every kinde of it.</hi> This ſaying I had alſo from the laſt words of the verſe, <hi>Walk humbly with thy God: theſe things he requires of the juſt, doing and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, mercy, loving, and a humble deportment in all thou doeſt:</hi> then I ſaid, <hi>Lord, make me humble:</hi> ſaid the Lord, <hi>I will make thee humble through ſufferings; the Lord thy God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun it in thee, when he manifested thy ſalvation to thee, to be freely given thee, making thee ſee thy ſelf, the worſt of ſinners; and he humbled thee more in Satans priſon, and he hath brought thee here to humble thee more; for he will teach thee much of his ſecrets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then my heart was melted as I was thus under divine ſpeakings in the Garden, and I ſaid, <hi>Lord, if thou wilt make me a partaker of more of that lovely clothing of humility; then, then, Lord, I will not matter what I ſuffer here in this world below:</hi> then the Lord ſaid, <hi>Thou muſt ſuffer many wayes:</hi> then I ſaid, <hi>Lord, balance me with thy word:</hi> the Lord ſaid, <hi>What word wouldſt thou have?</hi> I ſaid, <hi>What thou pleaſeſt:</hi> then the Lord ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt have the ſame word as I gave to my ſervant Abraham; I told him when he went he knew not whither, that I would be his ſhield and exceeding great reward,</hi> Gen. 15.1. <hi>And as I was,</hi> ſaid the Lord, <hi>to the father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſo I will be to the children, they having the ſame faith, as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Abraham had, I will give ſuch the ſame promiſes:</hi> then I ſaid, <hi>Lord, I fall ſhort of his faith.</hi> ſaid the Lord, <hi>I look not on the quantity
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93777:11"/>ſo much as at the quality; I looking at the truth of it, it bearing the ſame ſtamp with that of Abrahams, which was the ſtamp of divine power and Spirit: therefore take the ſame promiſe: thou art come into a ſtrange country, among many that don't affect thee, and thou art like to ſuffer by them; but fear not, I thy God have not onely given thee faith, as aſhield; but I am thy ſhield and exceeding great reward; I am a double ſhield to thee,</hi> ſaid the Lord, <hi>ſo I was to Abraham, a ſhield within a ſhield: therefore fear not any enemy; but look unto thy ſhield and buckler, and defence, for ſo Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah is to thee.</hi> And the Lord brought to me thoſe Scriptures that he gave me when he made me willing to go the journey, as that ſaying, He would go with me, and that bis Spirit and preſence ſhould accompany me, and that he would uphold me with the right hand of his righteouſneſs: which Scriptures were much enlarged on my Spirits, as I thus walked alone in the Garden: and I had ſuch ſweetneſs from the Lord through the Scriptures, that it made my heart much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with my journey, and my Spirit leapt within me, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced that I was come into a country where I ſhould ſuffer for the teſtimony of Jeſus; and I had at that time ſuch cordials from the Lord, that I could have walked many hours in that Garden; but Captain <hi>Langdons</hi> man came, and deſired me to walk into the room where his Maſters acquaintance were; <hi>For it may be they would not take it well,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>if I did not come and ſit in the room with them.</hi> I was very unwilling; for my communion in the Garden was ſo delightful to me; yet through much entreaty by him, I went. I told him, <hi>I could the better bear their ſowre countenances, and girding expreſſions, now I had drunk of divine cordials, then I could before, when I firſt ſaw them, at my coming into the houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So I went into the room among them, that did not care for my company, and I heard many expreſſions concerning viſions. I perceived what and who they aimed at; I ſate ſilent among them; there was Major <hi>Bawden</hi> and his Wife, they were ſtrangers then to me; but they ſpake very friend-like to me; and it was not in Tongue, but in Heart, as afterward appeared: and there was Mr. <hi>Vinſon</hi> and his Wife, my very loving friends they declared themſelves to be: Mrs. <hi>Vinſon</hi> came to me then, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93777:12"/>ſaid, <hi>Pray come to my houſe; for I entertain you upon a Scripture-a count, which adviſeth to be kinde to ſtrangers; and what gain they had in old time, that in entertaining ſtrangers, they enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Angels unawares.</hi> Thus ſhe inſtanced the Scripture, which made her to ſpeak to me, a poor, undeſerving crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be thus taken notice of; and indeed, I felt humility in my heart ſpringing up much, when ſhe thus ſpoke: I lookt on my ſelf unworthy of ſuch a word, or loving expreſſion to me; but my Father cauſed that friend, though a ſtranger, to ſhew me kindneſs.</p>
               <p>Again, further, This evening being ſpent, I went to my lodging, where the Lord ſmiled on me, and made it a lovely night, and I was no whit weary after ſo long a journey; but had refreſhing reſt; and in the morning Mrs. <hi>Langdon</hi> came to ſee me; but I had no minde to riſe out of my bed: and that day the Lord fill'd me with much joy and ſinging; and I was in the Spirit with my friends at <hi>London,</hi> who broke bread that day; and I was filled with apprehenſions of Chriſt, the eternal Sabbath, and the glorious Reſt, and the firſt-day-Reſurrection, how glorious all this was, meeting in Chriſt the Saviour and Deliverer from all bondage and inthralment: and my heart was much with my friends in that Ordinance of breaking bread; I partook of that ſweet ſupper with them in the Spirit. And thus I ſpent that firſt day that I came to <hi>Tregaſow,</hi> which was the firſt day of the firſt week that I took up my abiding there; much of Chriſts Death and Reſurrection was lively preſented to me, and I ſang forth his praiſes. And the ſecond day my heart was heat alſo with the flame of love, which many wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters cannot quench, as the ſpouſe ſaith in the Canticles, ſo I felt it; for all that day I had the Spirits flame, as I had the day before, it being their meeting day; thoſe particulars they firſt thought upon in their beginning that meeting, which were the uniting of Saints in that bond of love, as thoſe were in formerly, in the primitive times, and that they might be of one heart and one minde; and that knowledge might cover the earth, as water the ſea: and that <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi>-fulneſs might be brought in, and the Kingdom reſtored to this old <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:93777:12"/>which was the firſt married Wife, as it's recorded in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. And that Judges and Rulers might be as at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and as <hi>Samuel,</hi> and <hi>Gideon,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faithful ones, as is made mention of in Scripture. And I beſought the Lord for theſe things, and for the reign of Chriſt, in, and by which, theſe things ſhould be brought forth: and for this, every one, profeſſing the Lord, ought to pray. And thus I ſpent the ſecond day: and it was very ſweet to me, and fitted me for what I was to ſuffer in thoſe parts. And after that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond day, my heart was carried on very chearfully in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of the Lords preſence ſtill with me, and I had a great deal of tenderneſs from my friends I went down with, who were as a tender Father and Mother to me at all times; and in ſuffering, their tenderneſs and care of me exceeded, it abounded as my ſufferings abounded: and many that were at the firſt ſtrange in their carriages to me, after I had been there a while, they were very loving to me; and I had great kindneſs from the whole family, where I abode, till the wills of men fetcht me away with their Souldiers.</p>
               <p>Further, I ſhall give people to know, that after I had been a week and a few dayes there, I was deſired to go to <hi>Truro</hi> to hear the Lecture that was kept there every third day; ſo I did: and that morming before we went, there came a Letter, which after we had prayed, was read; wherein a Gentleman at <hi>Truro,</hi> invited Captain <hi>Langdon,</hi> and his Wife, and my ſelf to his houſe; the which invitation, we looked upon as anſwer of prayer, it coming ſo ſuitable to thoſe requeſts put up to the Lord that morning. And we went to <hi>Truro,</hi> and heard the Sermon; and that day, there preacht one Mr. <hi>Allen,</hi> a young man, who ſpake of many things from the I verſe of the 8 of the <hi>Romans.</hi> And when the Sermon was ended, we went home with Mrs. <hi>Hill</hi> to dinner, her husband having invited us by writing, the which I mentioned. And after dinner, there came many to ſee me, ſome out of good-will, and love to what they had heard was of God in me, and others came to gaze, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to catch at my words, ſo as to reproach me; but the Lord taught me how to ſpeak before them all: as in the preſence of the great God I ſpake, who is my Father, who alwaies ſhewed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93777:13"/>me kindneſs, and did then before thoſe ſeveral ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. I ſeeing many come into the room, and Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> a Teacher in thoſe parts, came in with his Wife, and another woman, ſo that being there, I thought to be ſilent; but ſome deſiring to have me ſpeak, I ſaid, <hi>I was loth to ſpeak before that critical-pated man, who would take my words and put his own ſence upon them, and ſo inſnare me;</hi> and it proved according as I ſaid: but when I had ſat a while, and ſaw ſo great a room full of people, who deſired I ſhould give an account for their edification and ſatisfactions, what God had done for my ſoul: there ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gone ſuch a rumour abroad concerning me, ſome ſaying one thing, and ſome another, it was therefore thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to ſpeak ſomething among that great company of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that was come to my friends houſe; and the Lord bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that word alſo, which is recorded by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. which is, <hi>to be ready to give an account at all times, when required, of the hope that is in me.</hi> And I being deſired to ſpeak, I thought it my duty, though at the firſt I refuſed; and when I began to ſpeak, I ſaid to Captain <hi>Langdon,</hi> who was then diſcourſing with that Mr. <hi>Power</hi> I mentioned, I ſaid, <hi>I remember a word from Mr. Bridges of Yarmouth, which was, That we muſt ſtill either be doing or receiving good: And,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>here is neither of theſe among us;</hi> and I repeated a word I told them Mr. <hi>Greenhil</hi> once ſaid to one whom he deſired, with many of that Congregation then preſent, who deſired experiences to be imparted to them, uſing that word of <hi>David</hi>'s, who ſaid, <hi>Come you that fear God, and I will tell you what God hath done for my ſoul:</hi> and then I took up <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſpeech he uſed before <hi>Agrippa,</hi> having been falſly accuſed by many, he declares the manner of his life from his youth, <hi>Acts</hi> 26. And ſo to others he ſaid, How he had walked in all good conſcience before the Lord unto that day he then ſpoke it, <hi>Acts</hi> 23. I uſed theſe words of the Apoſtle, and ſaid, <hi>This was his practice, when falſe rumours had gone concerning him; and being that people had reported many things which were very contrary concerning me, I thought it requiſite to acquaint them there preſent with the Lords dealings concerning me from my Childhood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I told them, the firſt conviction I had at nine yeers old; and how I remained under a formal work; and then how I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93777:13"/>was brought into a deſpairing condition, and was ſo a while: and then I told them, the Work of Free-grace on me, and the Teſtimony of the Spirit, bearing witneſs to my Spirit, that I was in union with the Father, Son and Spirit: and I told them of my deſertions and temptations, and of Satans many cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning wiles, and of freedom many times therefrom: and I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated my fit of ſickneſs which was cured in believing, that I had eight yeers ago; and I related the time and manner of my coming into Church order: and likewiſe I told them the firſt bringing of my Spirit into this extraordinary praying and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and viſions, was ſix weeks before <hi>Dunbar</hi>-fight in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which was a beginning three yeers before, but did not ſo much appear to the view of others: and I told them how I prayed againſt this publick-ſpiritedneſs; and how the Lord ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced me, from thoſe words in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27, 28. <hi>But God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world, to confound the wiſe; and God hath choſen the weak things of the world, to confound the things that are wights and baſe things of the world, and things which are deſpiſed, hath God choſen; yea, and things that are not, to bring to nought things that are.</hi> I could be contented to be made uſe of under theſe terms, as a fool, and baſe, and deſpiſed, and as a thing that is not. The Lord knows, I then ſtooped to his will to do with me as he pleaſed, when he ſet home this Scripture to my ſoul. And this I told them, and a great deal more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then; I will relate, for brevities ſake. I gave a Relation of my horrible fit I was in a yeer ago, and Sarans tyranny over me in that time, and the great freedom the Lord afforded me after that ſtorm, and the pourings out of the Spirit that hath been on my heart ever ſince. I declared viſions I had ſeven yeers ago, concerning four ſons of horns preſented to me, which related to four ſeveral changes of Powers one more fierce and ſharper ſtill then the other, and the little Horns worſt of all, more in its puſhings then the former. I ſpake of ſo many things, and ſo largely, that it took up the afternoon for the moſt part; ſo that before I ſpake much of my going to White-Hall, and praying and ſinging there, I broke forth into ſinging, my heart being ſo thorowly heated with diſcourſing of God, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo many hours. And I ſang and prayed a great part of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93777:14"/>that night; and when I gave over, my friends carried me in a chair into my chamber, and put me into bed, where I lay the remaining part of the night: and the next day ſang and prayed many hours: and many ſouls were much taken in that ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, concerning the preciouſneſs of Chriſt to them that believe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. from this Scripture, and many others, relating to Saints, and to ſinners not changed &amp; brought in to Chriſt: which day was ſo glorious to me, that Satan ſtirr'd up many againſt me afterwards, becauſe many were convinced, that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced before by their teachers; and ſome carnal ones were judiced before by their teachers; and ſome carnal ones were awed, convincing Scriptures came with ſuch authority; as that, <hi>Behold, ye deſpiſers, wonder, and periſh:</hi> and that word in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.22. <hi>Be ye not mockers, left your bands be made ſtrong.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Scriptures were ſpoken upon largely that day to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: and ſome ſaid afterwards, <hi>Which of all our Miniſters can hold out thus many hours without a cordial?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now when their Miniſters thought they ſhould loſe their fleece, they began to ſtir, like that maids masters ſpoken of in <hi>Acts</hi> 16.19. <hi>When her maſters ſaw what was done, they caught Paul and Sitas, and drew them into the marker-place into the Rulers:</hi> this was for the gift of healing, and calling out that unclean Spirit. All people obſerve how they loved ſooth-ſaying in thoſe times; and I would they did not in theſe dayes of more light. But I pray minde the Relation, That after that day wherein I was thus carried forth to ſpeak for Chriſt's intereſt, the Clergie, with all their might, rung their jangling bells againſt me, and called to the Rulers to take me up: that I heard was the ſpeech of Mr. <hi>Welſted:</hi> and others ſaid, <hi>The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would be drawn away, if the Rulers did not take ſome courſe with me.</hi> They were extremely afraid of loſing <hi>Diana</hi>'s repute. And after theſe two days ſpent at <hi>Truro,</hi> I returned to my place of abode at <hi>Tregaſow;</hi> but the Clergie gate information in many places of the Country, what an impoſtor, and a dangerous deceiver was come into <hi>Cornwal,</hi> that the people wondred what ſtrange kinde of creature was come into their Country; and thus they ſpit forth venome againſt me; but it did me no hurt, becauſe my Father made it work for good: my joy was not leſſened, but increaſed. And after a little while I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93777:14"/>was invited again to <hi>Truro,</hi> and I went to viſit Mrs. <hi>Hill,</hi> her husband being gone to <hi>London,</hi> ſhe prayed me to carry and bear her company. And after that I had ſat down a while, word was brought me, that there were two Warrants out for to take me, either at Captain <hi>Langdons,</hi> or at Major <hi>Bawdens:</hi> as for Major <hi>Bawdens,</hi> I was but once at his houſe; for I kept at my friends houſe I went down with, though the report was, I went from place to place, aſperſing the Government; I did not the one nor the other: I was but twice at <hi>Truro.</hi> I have told all the places I went to, while I remained at <hi>Tregaſow. This report of theirs is as falſe as the reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I will come to tell you how they acted againſt me: after I heard Warrants were out for me, I looked when they would come in to the houſe where I was, to take me. And many people came to ſee me. And one <hi>Haulbow</hi> a Miniſter, with whom I had ſome converſe, and he ſaid, <hi>I had fully ſatisfied him in his requeſt. And for his part,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>what he asked me, it was not ſo much for his own ſatisfaction, as for others, whom he could now ſatisfie:</hi> and he invited me to his houſe, and ſaid, <hi>I ſhould be welcome:</hi> and he told me, <hi>He would ſatisfie thoſe that had ſpoken againſt me, which were ſet on by falſe reports.</hi> And all theſe words, and many other more, amounted to juſt nothing; it was but Clergie-puff, which ſoon was gone like a puff of winde that is almoſt at an end, as ſoon as it riſeth, and ſo was his fair ſpeech to me: for I underſtand, ſince he hath reproached me and other friends that are of more worth then I, and yet this man ſpoke me ſo fair: but ſo much ſhall ſuffice as to him. I come again to tell you, that this day wherein I expected the Warrant for me, it came not: I that day found my timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, fearful nature work againſt me, what I ſhould do and ſay before the Magiſtrate, having never been before any in that kinde, to be accuſed by them; but the Lord ſeeing me not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to go before them, nor ſtrong enough, he would take me firſt into the Mount, and give me the preparations of the Sanctuary; and ſo he did before I was called before them. That night following this day that I have been ſpeaking of, there came about a dozen men and women to ſee me, and one Mr. <hi>Paul</hi> a miniſter, who had rode ten miles to that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93777:15"/>Town to underſtand aright concerning me, for that he had heard ſo many reports; and he deſired to be ſatisfied from my own mouth: ſo I related the Lords dealing with me, and what he had freely given me, for my own particular, and for others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit: and when I had done ſpeaking, I told him how I was like to ſuffer through falſe rumouts raiſed againſt me; &amp; I deſired him to pray with me: but he ſaid, <hi>He would joyne with me, if I would pray:</hi> I ſaid, <hi>I rather would hear him pray, and have a caſte of the cluster he had received of the Vine, Christ:</hi> ſo he prayed very ſweetly and ſpiritually: and when he had ended, it was about twelve a clock at night: and afterwards I ſpoke a little by way of diſcourſe, and was a little ſilent.</p>
               <p>Then the Lord made his Rivers flow, which ſoon broke down the Banks of an ordinary capacity, and extraordinarily mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Spirits into a praying and ſinging frame, and ſo they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained till morning-light, as I was told, for I was not capable of that: but when I had done, and was a while ſilent, I came to ſpeak weakly to thoſe about me, ſaying, <hi>I muſt go to bed, for I am very weak;</hi> and the men and women went away; and my friend that tended me, and ſome other maids, helpt me to bed, where I lay till the afternoon, they ſaid, ſilent. And that time I had a viſion of the Miniſters wife ſtirring againſt me; and ſhe was preſented to me, as one enviouſly bent againſt me, calling that falſity which ſhe underſtood not. And I ſaw the Glergie-man and the Jurors contriving an Indictment againſt me: and I ſaw my ſelf ſtand before them: in a viſion I ſaw this. And I ſang with much courage, and told them, <hi>I feared not them nor their doings, for that I had not deſerved ſuch u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But while I was ſinging praiſes to the Lord for his love to me, the Juſtices ſent their Conſtable to fetch me; who came, and ſaid, <hi>He muſt have me with him:</hi> and he pulled, and call'd me, they ſaid that were by, but I was not capable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: they ſaid, <hi>He was greatly troubled how to have me to his Maſter:</hi> they told him, <hi>He had better obey God then man: And his hand ſhooke,</hi> they ſaid, <hi>while he was pulling me.</hi> Then ſome went to the Juſtices, to tell them, <hi>I could not come.</hi> But they would not be pacified: ſome offered to be bound for my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93777:15"/>next day, if I were in a capacity; but this was refuſed, they would have me out of my bed, unleſs ſome would take their Oaths, that it would in danger my life to be taken out of my bed: which none could do, without they had loved to take falſe Oaths, like ſome others in thoſe parts. Then a friend perſwaded them to ſee whether they could put me out of that condition, and told them <hi>I was never known to be put out of it;</hi> ſo they came. Juſtice <hi>Launce,</hi> now a Parliament-man, was one of them, I was told. Theſe Juſtices that came to ferch me out of my bed, they made a great rumult, them and their followers, in the houſe, and ſome came up ſtairs, crying, <hi>A witch, a witch;</hi> making a great ſtir on the ſtairs; and a poor honeſt man rebuk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch that ſaid ſo, he was tumbled down ſtairs and beaten too, by one of the Juſtices followers: and the Juſtices made a great noiſe, in putting out of my chamber where I lay, many of my friends; and they ſaid, <hi>If my friends would not take me up, they would have ſome ſhould take me up:</hi> one of my friends told them, <hi>That they muſt fetch their ſilk gowns to do it them, for the poor would not do it.</hi> And they threatned much, but the Lord over-ruled them: they cauſed my eye-lids to be pull'd up, for the ſaid, <hi>I held them fast, becauſe I would deceive the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> they ſpake to this purpoſe. One of the Juſtices pincht me by the noſe, and cauſed my pillow to be pull'd from under my head, and kept pulling me, and calling me; but I heard none of all this ſtir and buſsle; neither did I hear Mr. <hi>Welſted,</hi> which I was told called to the Rulers, ſaying, <hi>A whip will fetch her up:</hi> and he ſtood at the Chamber door talking againſt me, and ſaid, <hi>She ſpeaks non-ſence:</hi> the women ſaid, <hi>Hearken, for you cannot hear, there is ſuch a noiſe:</hi> then he liſtened, and ſaid, <hi>Now ſhe hears me ſpeak, ſhe ſpeaks ſence.</hi> And this Clergie-man durſt not come, till the Rulers came, for then they ſay, The witches can have no power over them: ſo that one depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another, Rulers upon Clergie, and Clergie upon Rulers.</p>
               <p>And again, After they had made all the fury appear that the Lord permitted them to vent againſt me, they then went away, ſaying, <hi>She will fall in a trance, when we ſhall at any time call for her.</hi> The Lord kept me this day from their cruelty, which they had a good minde further to have let out againſt me, &amp; that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93777:16"/>witch tryer-woman of that Town, ſome would fain have had come with her great pin which ſhe uſed to thruſt into witches, to try them: but the Lord my God in whom I truſt, delivered me from their malice, making good that word to me in the <hi>Pſalms, The rage of man ſhall turn to thy praiſe, and the remnant of rages thou wilt reſtrain.</hi> Then further, to tell you how the Lord carried me in ſinging &amp; prayer after they were gone two hours, as I was told, and then I came to my ſelf; and being all alone, I bleſſed God for that quiet ſtill day that I had. And the Gentlewoman of the houſe coming into the chamber, I ſaid, <hi>Have I lain alone all this day? I have had a ſweet day:</hi> ſhe replied, and ſaid, <hi>Did not I hear the Justices there, and the uproare that was in my chamber?</hi> I ſaid, <hi>No.</hi> Then ſhe told me, how they dealt by her houſe, bringing in their followers, and what a noiſe they made. Then another friend asked me, <hi>Whether I did not hear that ſtir?</hi> I ſaid, <hi>No.</hi> They wondred, and ſo did I, when I heard the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, which is much more then I will write; for I don't take delight to ſtir in ſuch puddles, it's no pleaſant work to me; but that truth engageth me to let the world know, what men have acted againſt the pourings out of the Spirit in a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation beyond their underſtanding; they hearkened not to Scripture-advice, which would not have any judge that they know not.</p>
               <p>After that dayes tumult, at night, many came to catch at my words; and it was very probable, that the Rulers ſent ſome to watch for what could be had further againſt me: and there were two women, that they had got their names, who had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them to ſwear againſt me; and of this I ſhall further ſpeak when I come to it: but now I am telling of what paſt that night mentioned: many people ſpake much to me, asking me queſtions, the which the Lord helped me to anſwer. And my friends kept moſt part of that night in prayer on my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half. And many watched what they ſaid in prayer, for there were liſteners under the window, which fain would have had ſomething to have informed againſt them. There was great endeavouring to have found a Bill of Indictment againſt Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Langdon,</hi> but they could not; they could not vent their ſpleen, though they to the utmoſt deſired it, the Lord would
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93777:16"/>not let them have their evil deſires herein; for though they in this, would have brought him into contempt, yet they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured this that ſo I might want a ſurety, and then they had had what they deſired, which was, to have caſt me into the Goal. But to leave that, and to tell you, that I had the preſence of the Lord with me that night abundantly, and my ſleep was ſweeter then at other times; my ſiſter <hi>Langdon</hi> lay with me that night, and in the murning ſhe told me, <hi>That ſhe could not ſleep all night, for thinking of my going to the Seſſions that day:</hi> ſhe told me, <hi>She wandered I could ſleep ſo ſoundly all night:</hi> I told her, <hi>I never had a ſweater night in my liſe, and as for my going before the Rulers, I was no what afraid or thoughtful; for I had caſt my care upon the Lord, which I was perſwaded would ſpeak for me: therefore I was not troubled nor afraid; for the Lord ſaid to me, Fear not, be not diſmaied, I am thy God, and will ſtand by thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then I coſe up, and prepared to go before them at Seſſions-houſe; and walking out in the garden before I went, I was thinking what I ſhould ſay before the Juſtices; but I was taken off from my own thoughts quickly, through the word, <hi>Take no heed what thou ſhalt ſay; being brought before them for the Lord Chriſt's ſake, he will give thee words: doſt thou know what they will ask thee? therefore look to the Lord, who will give thee anſwers ſuitable to what ſhall be required of thee.</hi> So I was reſolved to caſt my ſelf upon the Lord, and his teaching: and though I had heard now the form of Bills run, and of that word <hi>Not guilty,</hi> according to the form of the Bill; yet I ſaid, <hi>I ſhall not remember to ſay thus, if the Lord do n't bid me ſay ſo; and if he bids me, I will ſay it.</hi> And this I thought, I would be nothing, the Lord ſhould have all the praiſe, it being his due. So I went, the Officer coming for me; and as I went along the ſtreet, I had followed me a andante of all maner of people, men and wemen, boyes and girls, which crowded after me; and ſome pull'd me by the arms, and ſtated me in the face, making wry-faces at me, &amp; ſaying, <hi>How do you now? how is it with you now?</hi> and thus they mocked and derided at me, as I went to the Seſſions; but I was never in ſuch a bleſſed ſelf-denying lambe like frame of Spirit in my life, as then; I had ſuch lovely apprehenſions of Chriſt's ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and of that Scripture which ſaith, <hi>He went as a ſheep,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93777:17"/>dumbe before the ſheerers, he opened not his mouth; and when reviled, he reviled not again.</hi> The Lord kept me alſo, ſo that I went ſilent to the Seſſions-houſe, which was much througed with people: ſome ſaid, <hi>The Seſſions-houſe was never ſo filled ſince it was a Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions-houſe;</hi> ſo that I was a gazing-ſtock for all ſorts of people: but I praiſe the Lord, this did not daunt me, nor a great deal more, that I ſuffered that day; for the eternal grace of Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah ſurrounded me, and kept me from harm, ſo way was made for me to draw neer, which ſtood lower then the Juſtices; and round the Table ſate the Lawyers and others that attended them, and I with my friends that went with me, ſtood by the Lawyers, and the Juſtices leaned over a rail, which railed them in together, onely I eſpied a Clergie-man at their elbow, who helped to make up their Indictment, ſo that he could not be abſent, though his Pulpit wanted him, it being a Faſt-day, ſet apart by Authority, which he broke without any ſcruple, that ſo he might keep cloſe to the work of accuſation; but though he and the witch-trying-woman looked ſtedfaſtly in my face, it did no way diſmay me, not the grim fierce locks of the Juſtice did not daunt me; for as ſoon as I beheld them, I remembred a dear friend to Chriſt, who ſmiled in the face of a great man, that looked fiercely on him, and ſate as a Judge to condemn him for the teſtimony of Jeſus; but this ſervant of the Lord looked chearfully all the time of his accuſations charged upon him; ſo I thinking upon that poſture of his before thoſe that acted againſt him, I begged the ſame chearfulneſs, and I had the ſame courage to look my Accuſers in the face: which was no carnal boldneſs, though they called it ſo.</p>
               <p>And when I came before them, <hi>Lobb</hi> being the Mourn of the Court, as he was fore-man of the Iury, he repreſented the whole Court, and he firſt demanded my name, and I told him; and he ſaid, <hi>Anna Trapnel, Here is a Bill of Indictment to be read, for you to give in your anſwer concerning:</hi> then Juſtice <hi>Lobb</hi> ſaid, <hi>Read the Bill:</hi> ſo it was read to me: and <hi>Lobb</hi> ſaid, <hi>Are you guilty, or not?</hi> I had no word to ſay at the preſent; but the Lord ſaid to me, <hi>Say Not guilty, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the form of the Bill;</hi> ſo I ſpoke it as from the Lord, who knew I was not guilty of ſuch an Indictment: then
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93777:17"/>ſaid <hi>Lobb, Traverſe the Bill to the next Aſſizes;</hi> ſo that was done: then <hi>Lobb</hi> ſaid, <hi>I muſt enter into bond for my appearance at the next Aſſizes:</hi> unto which I agreed: then they demanded Sureties: ſo I deſired Captain <hi>Langdon</hi> and Major <hi>Bawden</hi> to be my Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, unto which they were willing: ſo there were two Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognizances drawn, one for my appearance, and the other bound me to the good behaviour; and I was entred into both the Recognizances 300 <hi>l.</hi> and my Sureties as much, to both the Recognizances. And this being done, they whiſpered a while: and I thought they had done with me at that time; ſo they had, if they had gone according to true Law, which was, not to have brought their Interrogatories then; but the report was, That I would diſcover my ſelf to be a witch when I came before the Juſtices, by having never a word to anſwer for my ſelf; for it uſed to be ſo among the witches, they could not ſpeak before the Magiſtrates, and ſo they ſaid, it would be with me; but the Lord quickly defeated them herein, and cauſed many to be of another minde. Then <hi>Lobb</hi> ſaid, <hi>Tender her the book which was written from ſomething ſaid at</hi> White-Hall: ſo the book was reached out to me: and Juſtice <hi>Lobb</hi> ſaid, <hi>What ſay you to that book? will you own it? is it yours?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. T. <hi>I am not careful to anſwer you in that matter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then they ſaid, <hi>She denies her book.</hi> Then they whiſpered with thoſe behinde them. Then ſpake Juſtice <hi>Lobb</hi> again, and ſaid, <hi>Read a viſion of the horns out of the book:</hi> ſo that was read: then Juſtice <hi>Lobb</hi> ſaid, <hi>What ſay you to this? is this yours?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. T. <hi>I am not careful to anſwer you in that matter, touching the whole book, as I told you before, ſo I ſay again: for what was ſpoken, was at</hi> White-Hall, <hi>at a place of concourſe of people, and neer a Counſel, I ſuppoſe wiſe enough to call me into queſtion if I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, and unto them I appeal; but though it was ſaid,</hi> I appealed unto Caeſar, and unto Caeſar ſhould I go; yet I have not been brought before him which is called Caeſar: ſo much by the by. <hi>Again,</hi> I ſaid, <hi>I ſuppoſed they had not power to queſtion me for that which was ſpoke in another county:</hi> they ſaid, <hi>Yea, that they had.</hi> Then the book was put by; and they again whiſpered.</p>
               <p>Then Juſtice <hi>Lobb</hi> asked me about my coming into that Country, <hi>How it came to paſs, that I came into that Country.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:93777:18"/>
               <p>I anſwered, <hi>I came as others dad, that were minded to go into the Country.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lobb. <hi>But why did you come into this Country?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. T. <hi>Why might not I come here, as well as into another Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lobb. <hi>But you have no lands, nor livings, nor acquaintance to come to in this Country.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. T. <hi>What though? I had not I am a ſingle perſon, and why may I not be with my friends anywhere?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lobb. <hi>I underſtand you are not married.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. T. <hi>Then having no hinderance, why may not I go where I pleaſe, if the Lord ſo will?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then ſpoke Juſtice <hi>Launſe. But did not ſome deſire you to come down?</hi> And this <hi>Lobb</hi> asked me too: but I told them, <hi>I would accuſe none, I was there to anſwer, as to what they ſhould charge my own particular with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Launſe ſaid, <hi>Pray Miſtriſs tell us, what moved you to come ſuch a journey?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A.T. <hi>The Lord gave me leave to come, asking of him leave, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therever I went: I uſed ſtill to pray for his direction in all I do: and ſo I ſuppoſe ought you,</hi> I ſaid.</p>
               <p>Juſtice Launſe. <hi>But pray tell us, what moved you to come ſuch a journey?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. T. <hi>The Lord moved me, and gave me leave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Launſe. <hi>But had you not ſome of extraordinary impulſes Spirit, that brought you down? pray tell us what thoſe were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. T. <hi>When you are capable extraordinary of impulſe of Spirit, I will tell you; but I ſuppoſe you are not in a capacity now:</hi> for I ſaw how deridingly he ſpoke: and for anſwering him thus, he ſaid, <hi>I was one of a bold Spirit; but he ſoon took me down;</hi> ſo himſelf ſaid: but ſome ſaid, <hi>It took them down:</hi> for the Lord carried me ſo to ſpeak, that they were in a hurry and confuſion, and ſometimes would ſpeak all together, that I was going to ſay, <hi>What are you like women, all ſpeakers, and no hearers?</hi> but I ſaid thus, <hi>What do you ſpeak all at a time? I cannot anſwer all, when ſpeaking at once; I appeal to the civillest of you,</hi> and I directed my ſpeech to Juſtice <hi>Lobb,</hi> who ſpake very moderately, and gave me a civil anſwer, ſaying, <hi>You are not acquainied with the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93777:18"/>manner of the Court, which is to give in their ſayings.</hi> A.T. <hi>But I cannot anſwer all at once; indeed I do not know the manner of the Court, for I never was before any till now.</hi> Juſtice Lobb. <hi>You propheſie againſt</hi> Truro. A.T. <hi>Indeed I pray againſt the ſins of the people of</hi> Truto, <hi>and for their ſouls welfare; are you angry for that?</hi> Lobb. <hi>But you muſt not judge Authority; but pray for them, and not ſpeak ſo ſuſpiciouſly of them:</hi> and more to this purpoſe he ſpoke to me. A.T. <hi>I will take up your word, in which you ſaid, I was not to judge: you ſaid well; for ſo ſaith the Scripture,</hi> Who art thou that judgeſt anothers mans ſervant? to his own maſter he ſtandeth or falleth; yea, he ſhall be holden up, for God is able to make him ſtand: <hi>but you have judged me, and never heard me ſpeak: you have not dealt ſo well by me as</hi> Agrippa <hi>dealt by</hi> Paul: <hi>though</hi> Agrippa <hi>was an Heathen, he would have</hi> Paul <hi>ſpeak before he gave in his judgement concerning him.</hi> Juſtice Tregegle. <hi>Oh you are a dreamer!</hi> A.T. <hi>So they called</hi> Joſeph, <hi>therefore I wonder not that you call me ſo.</hi> Juſtice Selye ſaid, <hi>You knew we were with you yeſterday.</hi> A.T. <hi>I did not.</hi> Juſtice Selye. <hi>He which is the Major ſaid, you will not ſay ſo.</hi> A.T. <hi>I will ſpeak it, being it's truth.</hi> He ſaid, <hi>Call the women, that will witneſs they heard you ſay, You knew we were with you; and he pulled out a writing, and named their names, calling to ſome to fetch them.</hi> A.T. <hi>You may ſuborne falſe witneſſes againſt me, for they did ſo againſt Chriſt:</hi> and I ſaid, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce your witneſſes.</hi> Juſtice Sely. <hi>We ſhall have them for you at next Aſſizes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They put it off long enough, becauſe one was fallen in a ſound before the got out of the houſe were ſhe dwelt; and the other was come into the Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons-houſe: and Mrs. <hi>Groſe</hi> a gentlewoman of the town ſtanding by her that was their falſe witneſs, ſaid, <hi>Wilt thou take an oath thus? take heed what thou doſt, it's a dangerous thing to take a falſe oath;</hi> and ſhe ran out of the Seſſions-houſe: this was credibly reported. And here ended their witneſſes that they had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured againſt me as to that. There was a ſouldier that ſmiled to hear how the Lord carried me along in my ſpeech: and Juſtice <hi>Selye</hi> called to the Jailor to take him away, ſaying, <hi>He laughed at the Court.</hi> He thought him to be one of my friends: and for his cheerful looking, the Jailor had like to have had him: then I ſaid, <hi>Scripture ſpeaks of ſuch who</hi> make a man an offender for a word; <hi>but you make a man an offender for a look.</hi> They greatly buſsled, as if they would have taken him away; but this was quickly ſquaſht, their heat as to this laſted not long. In the mean time the other <hi>Sely</hi> was talking to Major <hi>Bawden,</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering ſuch a man as he, who had been ſo well reputed for a judicious, ſober, underſtanding man, ſhould hearken to me: many words were uſed to him to that purpoſe: I ſaid, <hi>Why might not he and others, try all things, and hold faſt that which is beſt.</hi> But they ſtill caſt grim looks on me: and they had a ſaying to Major <hi>Bawden,</hi> and to Captain <hi>Langdon</hi> then, whom they derided in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſent from <hi>Truro</hi> by ſome of their learned Court, which wrote, that Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Langdon</hi> and Major <hi>Bawden</hi> ſtood up, and made a learned defence. They had indeed ſuch learning from the Spirit of wiſdom and of a ſound minde, which the Jurors and their companions were not able to contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, their ſpeech and whole deportment was ſo humble and ſelf denying, and ſo ſeaſoned with the ſalt of grace, which their flaſhy unſavory ſpirits could not endure; thoſe that are raiſed from the dung-hill, and ſet on thrones, cannot ſit there without vaunting, and ſhewing their fools coat of many colours, as envie, and pride, and vain glory; theſe and other colours
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93777:19"/>they ſhow, which delights not King Jeſus nor his followers. Juſtice <hi>Lobb</hi> told me, <hi>I made a diſturbance in the town:</hi> I asked, <hi>Wherein?</hi> he ſaid, <hi>By drawing ſo many people after me:</hi> I ſaid, <hi>How did I draw them?</hi> he ſaid, <hi>I ſet open my Chamber-doors and my windows for people to hear.</hi> A.T. <hi>That's a very unlikely thing, that I ſhould do ſo; for I prayed the maid to lock my chamber-door when I went to bed, and I did not riſe in the night ſure to open it:</hi> I ſaid, <hi>Why may not I pray with many people in the room, as well as your profeſſing women that prays be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men and women, ſhe knowing them to be there; but I know not that there is any body in the room when I pray: and if you indite one for praying, why not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? why are you ſo partial in your doings?</hi> Juſtice <hi>Lobb. But you don't pray ſo as others.</hi> A.T. <hi>I pray in my chamber.</hi> Juſtice <hi>Travel. Your chamber!</hi> A. T. <hi>Yea, that it's my chamber while I am there, through the pleaſure of my friends.</hi> They uſed more words to me, ſometimes ſlighting and mockingly they ſpoke, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſeeming to adviſe me to take heed how I ſpoke and prayed ſo again. Many ſuch kinde of words Juſtice <hi>travel</hi> uſed, and Juſtice <hi>Lobb.</hi> And one thing I omitted in telling you, when I told you how I anſwered Juſtice <hi>Launſe;</hi> I ſhould have told you how <hi>I</hi> ſaid to him, <hi>If he would know what the ordinary impulſe of Spirit was, that I had to bring me into that country, I would tell him;</hi> ſo I related the Scriptures, as that in the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and in the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> how the preſence and Spirit of the Lord ſhould be with me, and he would uphold me and ſtrengthen me with the right hand of his righteouſneſs: he anſwered, <hi>Such impulſe was common, they hoped they had that, they were not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of ſuch impulſe of Spirit;</hi> much to this effect was ſpoken. I ſeeing they were very willing to be gone, I ſaid, <hi>Have you done with me?</hi> anſwer was, <hi>I might now go away;</hi> but I ſaid, <hi>Pray what is it to break the good behaviour you have bound me over to? I know not what you may make a breaking of it: is it a breaking the good behaviour, to pray and ſing?</hi> Juſtice <hi>travel</hi> ſaid, <hi>No, ſo I did it at the habitation where I abode. It's well,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>you will give leave it ſhall be anywhere.</hi> I ſaid, <hi>I will leave one word with you, and that is this: A time will come when you and I ſhall appear before the great Judge of the tribunal ſeat of the moſt High, and then I think you will hardly be able to give an account for this days work before the Lord, at that day of true judgement:</hi> ſaid Tregegle, <hi>Take you no care for us.</hi> So they were willing to have no more diſcourſe with me.</p>
               <p>And as I went in the croud, many ſtrangers were very loving and careful to help me out of the croud: and the rude multitude ſaid, <hi>Sure this woman is no witch, for ſhe ſpeaks many good word, which the witches could not.</hi> And thus the Lord made the rude rabble to juſtifie his appearance; for in all that was ſaid by me, I was nothing, the Lord put all in my mouth, and told me what I ſhould ſay, and that from the written word, he put it in my memory and mouth: ſo that I will have nothing aſcribed to me, but all honor and praiſe given to him whoſe right it is, even to Jehovah, who is the King that lives for ever. I have left our ſome things that I thought were not ſo material to be written: and what I have written of this, it's to declare as much as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to take off thoſe falſities and contrary reports that are abroad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my ſufferings, ſome making it worſe then it was, and ſome ſaying, <hi>It was little or nothing.</hi> Now to inform all peoples judgements, I have thought it meet to offer this relation to the worlds view, and with as much covering as I can of Saints weakneſſes herein, praying the Lord to forgive them; and as for the Lords enemies, that he would confound them; but as for my enemies, I ſtill pray.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:93777:19"/>
               <p>I now ſhall declare how God ſhewed me kindneſſe further. I rode home with my friends to <hi>Tregaſow,</hi> that day, rejoycing that I was counted worthy to be ſo reproachfully dealt by, for ſpeaking in the Lord Chriſts behalf, in prayer and praiſes; and I remained very chearfull, continuing in prayer and Thankſgiving, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſpirituall ſongs unto the Lord; but about ten dayes after, the Souldiers of the Fox came to take me, and the day before they come, it being the firſt day of the the week, I went to hear Mr. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> who preached hard by where I abode, one whom the Clergy would fain have had to have ſpoke againſt me, but he ſaid, he would not; they then called him my diſciple, and laughed and jeered at him when he came among them, on their Lecture dayes. They u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to meet at an Ordinary where many of the Clergy and others dined together: while I was in theſe parts, the Clergy and others made me their Table and Pulpit talk, and would have had Mr. <hi>Frances</hi> to have done as they did, but he refuſed; and hath ſince, I hear, left the place where he preached when I was in thoſe parts. But I return where I left, in telling you how I was the day before that the Souldiers came for me, I was very heavy in my ſpirit, as I ſat at dinner with my friends, and I was very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſhed tears; and being loath my friends ſhould ſee me, I held from weeping, as much as I could, for I thought they would think that I took ſomething unkindly, but truly I could not, for I had as much love from every one in the Family, as could be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but I was very ſad, and I roſe from the Table where I dined, and went and took my Bible, wherein the Lord refreſhed me, and in the afternoon I went to hear, and came home, and went into the garden to walk alone; and Captain <hi>Langdon</hi> coming into the Garden, I diſcourſed a while with him; and I ſaid, ſure my <hi>London</hi> friends pray me up to <hi>London,</hi> and when I come there, I will write of <hi>Cornwell, Cornhell</hi> in the Weſt. He ſaid you might have ſuffered at <hi>London,</hi> but not as here ſaid I; for here they deal very uncivilly, and unchriſtian like by me: well ſaid I, the Lord ſend me to <hi>London,</hi> for I ſhall count it a great mercy to ſee their faces again, I had ſaid a <hi>Bridewell</hi> among them ſhall be ſweet to me, and ſo the Lord made it: I that night was perſwaded, my work was done in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and that I ſhould erelong ſee <hi>London,</hi> yet being I was bound over to the Seſſions, which was not to be till <hi>Auguſt,</hi> ſo that I was to have carried many weeks by the Juſtices
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93777:20"/>order, but they could not bear ſo much praving, ſo long a time to be in their parts, therefore they haſted their Letters to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell at <hi>White Hall,</hi> to ſend their order down for me, having a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours Troop ſo near, to agitate their buſineſſe. And the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours was afraid of his Souldiers, he commands them to their Colours: and Enſign <hi>Raundle,</hi> he muſt be caſt out of his place, for inviting his old friend Captain <hi>Longdon,</hi> and his wife, and his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and me, to come with them to his houſe. And the Souldiers were charged to keep me out of <hi>Tregny,</hi> that is, three miles from <hi>Tregaſow,</hi> where a poore tempted ſoul was, that would fain have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained me at her Houſe, and this work the Fox made in his fortified places; but the poore who are rich in faith, prayed for me in thoſe parts, and ſome I never ſaw, about ten miles from the place where I was, who hearing of my trouble, improved their intereſt with the Lord for me; their faith and prayer, did me more good than all the gold, or filver, or favours of great men could have done me.</p>
               <p>I ſhall relate now further concerning that night before the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers took me; I ſaw in my ſleep Souldiers come to take me, and I rode towards <hi>London</hi> with them very joyfully, and in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I made me ready, and went down ſtairs; and there was a friend came to ſee Captain <hi>Langdon,</hi> ſo I went up into my Chamber, to write to <hi>London,</hi> and I was thinking of that I ſaw in my ſleep, that I was riding from the Houſe towards <hi>London;</hi> and I alſo was was marvelling, that my ſpirit was ſo heavy the day before, and this ſaying I had in my heart, Chriſt was heavy before the hour; before they came to take him he was in an Agony: ſaid I Lord, what manner of ſaying is this? and as I was pondering upon it, my ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Langdon</hi> came up into my Chamber, very ſad, and ſaid, ſiſter, pray thee do not be frighted, why? ſaid I, what is the matter? there is ſaid ſhe half a Troop of Horſe come to take thy body, or my husbands; there was half a dozen ſouldiers, and they made ſuch a clutter, ſhe thought they had been a greater number, but there was a number great enough to take a Poore ſilly maid. So I rejoyced, and ſaid I am not troubled, for I ſhall ſee my friends at <hi>London;</hi> ſhe ſaid to Miſtris <hi>Frances</hi> her mothers maid, pray thee Miſtris <hi>Frances,</hi> take my ſiſter, and eſcape into the wood hard by by the houſe, they cannot find her there; but I ſaid, I will not make my ſelf guilty by flying away, for I have not broke any Law,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93777:20"/>whereby man ſhould do thus, and as long as God is on my ſide, ſaid I, men nor devils ſhall not affright me; and the Lord gave me that word of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Shall ſuch a man as I flee?</hi> So ſaid I to them, <hi>Shall ſuch a one as I flee?</hi> who have lived with the Lord, all my dayes, and have been couragious for Chriſt hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, I will not now flinch through the ſtrength of the Lord keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me, and I know he will keep me: then many in the Family came, and the neighbours, and wept about mee, but I was no whit daunted. The Miniſter of the Pariſh came, and ſaid he would not wiſh me to go down, without they would ſhew an order, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, what order have they brought, none but Captain <hi>Foxe's</hi> let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they told me, that ſaid I, is enough; for there is the <hi>Foxe's</hi> claws to pin me to <hi>Plimouth,</hi> ſo through perſwaſions, I run down ſtairs, where I heard the Souldiers very rough in their words, and they ſaid they would not tarry a moment for me, and they would have me by foul means, if I refuſed to go; they threatned much what they would do, the Quartermaſter was very high in his words. So when I had heard them bluſter thus a while, I ſtept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, many of my friends being with them, I coming into the room, ſtood by them, and ſaid, friend, whom do you ſeek? ſpeaking to the Quartermaſter: he ſaid, is this the Lady? I ſaid, I do not know what you mean by Lady, but that is a Souldiers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement: I pray, whom do you ſeek? So he asked whether my name was <hi>Anna Trapnell,</hi> I ſaid, I ſuppoſe that is my name; then he ſaid, I demand your body; ſaid I take it, if it will do you any good, I am ready to go with you: then he was very reſpectfull, and ſaid, he would ſhew me all the courteſie and civility that lay in his power, I thankt him and ſaid, they could not harm me; for my God would not ſuffer them; then they ſaid, they would wait til I was fitted to go, and they tarried till the afternoon: And when we had dined, I took my leave of my dear loving friends, and departed, riding behind a friend that came to ſee Captain <hi>Langdon,</hi> who put off his Journey that he was riding, and offered to carry me, and Captain <hi>Langdons</hi> man, and his mothers maid, they ſent mith me, and I went filled with the joy of the Lord: and that day, ſome two or three miles off, I met with ſome dear friends, who bore me company a while, but I had ſo much of the refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God, which quickly overcame my ordinary capacity, and I felt not the trotting of the horſe, nor minded any thing but the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93777:21"/>ſpiritual communion, that I was in with the Lord; and ſo I rode praying, all the firſt dayes Journey, till I came to <hi>Foy</hi>-Town, where they took me down off the horſe, and ſet me in a chair, but I came not to my capacity to ſpeak a great while, and when I look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, and ſaw many men, women and children about me, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on a high wall, right over where I ſate, I was amazed to ſee ſo many people, and not knowing where I was, but at length I ſpake to them in Scripture language, the which they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened to, and when I went away, they gave a great ſhout; the people ſaid, they uſed to do ſo at ſome ſtrange ſight: ſo they led me into the Boat, for we went over a paſſage, and many men and women went over with us from that Town, and the room was full of people, where I lodged, ſome came to gaze on me, and ſome came in love to the Lord Jeſus, to hear experiences, and ſome temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſouls were much refreſhed, and rejoyced much to ſee me there, though not as I was, a priſoner; they wept for me as to that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and I ſate up moſt part of the night at <hi>Foy,</hi> and begged thoſe that came to jeer at me, that they would conſider the wrong they did to their poore ſouls, and had Scripture very ſuitable to thoſe I ſpoke; I asked them what they came to ſee, I was but as a reed ſhaken with the wind; I was a ſimple creature, onely divine wiſdome was pleaſed to make uſe of the ſimple, and to call them to him, to ſhew them his love, to chuſe ſuch to do him ſervice, and I ſaid, I am a poore ſorry reed, but divine power, and the wind that Chriſt told <hi>Nichodemus,</hi> in the 3. of <hi>John</hi> the 8. which bloweth where it liſteth, that wind ſaid I, hath taken a ſilly creature, and hath made her underſtand its ſound, that which <hi>Nichodemus</hi> a great Rabbi, could not tell what to make of; ſo that I prayed them that derided, that they would have a care, and that they therein would conſider the ſaying of Chriſt in the 25. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> who ſaid, what they did to his, they did to him, though I be one of the worſt of Chriſts little ones, yet ſaid I, he will own me, where ever I am: I beſeech ſinners to love Chriſt, who was the chiefeſt of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and I ſpoke how the Church ſet him out in the <hi>Canticles;</hi> and I told them, though they made me a by-word, and a reproach, yet I would pray for their Souls: I told them I came not into the Countrey to be ſeen, and taken notice of, but I came with my friends. I deſired Chriſt and the beauty of holineſſe might be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of, ſo that others thereby might be taken with Chriſt;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93777:21"/>and that I might be onely a voyce, and Chriſt the ſound; I ſpake much to prophane ſinners, and to the civilized ones that they would eye the new Covenant, which admits of no condition, nor qualification, nor preparation, but is a free Covenant to ſinners, as ſinners, that if they venture their ſouls thereupon, it will at the moment change, and make them hate ſin, and all manner of evil, and cleave to that good the Scripture makes mention of; then to the tempted was ſpoken from <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.18. for in that Chriſt ſuffered being tempted, he is able to ſuccour them that are tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and unto them were experiences ſpoken, how greatly Chriſt was ſenſible of the temptations of his people, and his ſuccourings were great, and his ſympathizing much: So I related what bowels of compaſſion from the Lord I found herein, though when I was murmuring againſt the Lord, who I thought dealt roughly by me, I ſaid with <hi>Jonas,</hi> I do well to do thus, as he ſaid, <hi>I do well to be angry:</hi> So I was very peeviſh, thinking that Satan would have made an end of me. I ſaid with <hi>Jonah, I do well to be angry to the death.</hi> I prayed tempted ſouls to hearken to Chriſt, and not to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; ſome tempted ſouls there wept bitterly, and the next day came again, and accompanied me out of that Town: So I took my leave, they begging to hear from me, and deſired my welfare.</p>
               <p>Then I rode to a place called <hi>Lew,</hi> where I deſired to ſtay an hour, but it was hard to be obtained of the Quartermaſter, though he had promiſed Captain <hi>Langdon</hi> that I ſhould ſee ſome friends there; yet when I came there, he was afraid I ſhould have broke out into prayer there, and ſo have ſtaied him longer then he would, but I and my friends did ſo intreat him, that he gave me leave to go with a Souldier with me, to bring me quickly back to him again, he ſtaying a little way off, and ſaid that I ſhould have no body come into the houſe that I went to; this he charged the Souldier, ſo that coming to that houſe I went to, there I was entertained with much love, and ſome few did hear of my being there, and came to ſee me, and watched for my coming out. I had ſome diſcourſe with a blind man there, who had much of the light of the Lord in his ſoul, and his words were ſo ſavoury, that my heart was quickned by the Lord in that diſcourſe I had with this ſeeing ſoul, though blind outwardly; and I ſtayed among them a while, till I was full of joy in the ſight of theſe dear friends; ſo that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hurried away by the Souldiers, I brake forth into tears, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93777:22"/>ſaid, the time will come that ſpirituall communion ſhall not be interrupted; and indeed the thoughts of Eternity melted my heart, that I ſaid, I weep not for ſorrow, but my tears flow from apprehenſions of communion with the Lord, and thoſe glorified Saints there; if Saints on earth did ſo take up my heart, I ſaid, what will that company be to me, in heaven, ſure it will be joy to the full: So thoſe dear ſouls went with me out of the Town, and then bid farewell, ſaying, they were ſory, I could ſtay no longer with them, ſo I parted, and rode towards <hi>Plimmouth</hi> with very much of the Lords preſence.</p>
               <p>And when I came to <hi>Plimmouth,</hi> after the Quartermaſter had been to inform that <hi>I</hi> was coming, he came and had me up to the Fort, two of the other Souldiers going with me, and four others who were my friends, theſe bore me company to the Fort, and when I came into the Lieutenants houſe, <hi>I</hi> ſate down a while, and he told me <hi>I</hi> was committed to his charge as his priſoner, for that Major <hi>Sanders</hi> was not there unto whom the Letter was ſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning me; ſo after a few words had paſt between us, <hi>I</hi> defired him to let me hear the order read; ſo he read it, wherein was expreſt that <hi>I</hi> was to be ſent from thence in the firſt States Ship that went to <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and ſo to be ſent from thence to the Counſell; and when this was read, after a little while ſpent in diſcourſe, Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>Lark,</hi> in whoſe houſe <hi>I</hi> was a priſoner; he asked me whether <hi>I</hi> would go up ſtairs and ſee my chamber, unto which <hi>I</hi> was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and my four friends went up with me, and I bleſſe the Lord, <hi>I</hi> never was in ſo bleſſed a frame in my life, being in an ordinary capacity, the which <hi>I</hi> was in a while, but at length the Lord wound me up higher; and as <hi>I</hi> was telling you, that coming into my chamber, <hi>I</hi> found the Lord Chriſt opening his love to me from that Scripture, in <hi>Hoſea</hi> the 2.19. <hi>I</hi> have betrothed thee to my ſelf in mercy and loving kindneſſe for ever. And <hi>I</hi> had ſome inlargement upon that, and likewiſe from Scripture expreſſions in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> and in <hi>Habbakuk,</hi> but <hi>I</hi> omit writing what ſweet unfoldings <hi>I</hi> had therein from the Lord, becauſe <hi>I</hi> intend if the Lord will give me opportunity to write down the cordialls of the Lord, which <hi>I</hi> had in my confinement by man, in a book wherein <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſet out Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans priſon, the which I was in a year before mans priſon, that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry month that I was ſet at liberty from Satans confinement, men confined me, which was the ſecond month called <hi>April,</hi> which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93777:22"/>was a year after that horrible pit of Satans, the which <hi>I</hi> lay in, from the beginning of <hi>February,</hi> till the beginning of <hi>April,</hi> about nine weeks, but I have been in mans priſon 15. weeks, yet that was to me much eaſier, then a ſhortertime in Sataus clutches.</p>
               <p>But <hi>I</hi> return to the Relation of my firſt coming into priſon, <hi>I</hi> was exceedingly tranſported in my ſpirits, and <hi>I</hi> was as if I had been to die preſently, nothing was in my thoughts but divine boſome, which made me bid farewell to all creatures: <hi>I</hi> thought <hi>I</hi> could have imbraced death, though it ſhould be never ſo gaſtly, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly tendered to me, I never had ſuch joy in the thoughts of death, and <hi>I</hi> ſaid to Lieutenant <hi>Lark,</hi> pray Sir, let me have the liberty to be private a while with my friends, who came with me, the which he granted, and he went down from us, then <hi>I</hi> ſaid, this is the greateſt preferment as ever I had, to be honoured with a priſon for Chriſt, this is honour ſaid <hi>I</hi> indeed, <hi>I</hi> now can take my leave of all things under the Sun, and ſee all things vanity, and poor em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty nothings; and <hi>I</hi> ſaid farewell all creatures, and welcome Chriſt, then <hi>I</hi> deſired my friends that we might pray together be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they departed; for <hi>I</hi> ſaid it was the beſt work to begin my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment in ſpirituall Communion, then we prayed, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome time ſpent in prayer, the Sonne of righteouſneſſe ſhone ſo hot on my ſpitits, that <hi>I</hi> could not forbear ſinging forth his prariſe; and my friends told me, that <hi>I</hi> was three hours on my knees, praying, and praiſing, that <hi>I</hi> felt no pain nor weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe, though <hi>I</hi> had journeyed ſo far. They took me off my knees, and ſet me in a chair, where <hi>I</hi> ſat ſome hours after in ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and then was ſilent, and ſome women put me to bed, where <hi>I</hi> lay praying and ſinging the other part of that night, while mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and the maid that tended me ſaid, ſhe ſate in the bed, wiping away the tears from my eyes, which ſhe ſaid came exceeding faſt all night, as <hi>I</hi> ſung and prayed. And truly the Sonne from on high had very much thawed my heart, and I prayed and ſung after that night, four dayes, and ſometimes wrapt up in ſilence with the Lord, beholding his glory in viſions, and on the laſt day of that week, <hi>I</hi> ſpoke to ſome ſea-men and others that came to viſit me, telling them the Lords kindneſſe to me in my troubles in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and other experiences <hi>I</hi> related to them, and the Lord knows <hi>I</hi> did ſpeak of theſe things to them that they might be more in love with Chriſt, who let out himſelf to a poore creature ſo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93777:23"/>extraordinarily. And the next day after, it was the firſt day of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other week, ſome would fain have had me gone to have heard the word preached that day, but it could not be granted that <hi>I</hi> ſhould go out of the Fort; and indeed <hi>I</hi> was very weak, having lain four dayes and five nights, and came not out of my bed, nor took no refreſhing creature, ſave a draught of ſmall beer or ſyder, and ſometimes eat a little piece of toaſt out of it, and this was but once at a night, and not every night neither; and this was for ſixt dayes: and this firſt day that <hi>I</hi> roſe out of my bed, <hi>I</hi> lay down again quickly, and <hi>I</hi> took a Bible, and read the 11. Chapter of <hi>Luke,</hi> and the 12. Chapter, and my heart was much taken with the words there that Chriſt ſpoke to them, and the Lord applyed much to me of what Chriſt ſpoke concerning their calling of him <hi>Beelzebub:</hi> and if they dealt ſo with Chriſt, <hi>I</hi> thought it was but as Chriſt was dealt with, to be called Devil, and that ſaying <hi>I</hi> was poſſeſt with a lying ſpirit, but this was made very eaſie, when <hi>I</hi> conceived Chriſt bare a great deal more, and after that theſe Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were faſtened and knit to my heart, the Lord making them mine. <hi>I</hi> admiring at the ſufferings of Chriſt, and at his patience, and <hi>I</hi> continued ſinging moſt part of that day, concerning the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and my intereſt therein, and <hi>I</hi> ſang as to the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of many who lived in the Fort, and concerning my paſſage on the ſea that <hi>I</hi> ſhould have; ſpeaking of the Lords appearances that <hi>I</hi> ſhould have there, and the Joy and Triumph I ſhould be in, in all my impriſonment time, and the next day after this, it being the ſecond day of the week, I had been a priſoner ſeven dayes, and this was the eighth day from the Souldiers taking me, ſo I that day at night, after the hours ſpent with my friends at <hi>London,</hi> which I knew kept that day in part, in prayer, ſo did I, though abſent in body from them; and at night as I ſaid before, <hi>I</hi> went down and diſcourſed with Lieutenant <hi>Lark</hi> a while, and after <hi>I</hi> had ſhewed him two Letters which <hi>I</hi> had written to <hi>London,</hi> that he ſaw there was none of that which is called Treaſon in them, then <hi>I</hi> wiſhed him a good night, and <hi>I</hi> went to bed, and he the next day rode out of Town to fetch his wife, who was with her friends in the Countrey, and in his abſence, Enſign <hi>Owen</hi> was my keeper, and he was very carefull to fulfill his office, and was loath to let in my friends to ſee me, but charged them at the gate with treſpaſſe, if they let in any of my friends, ſaying, they had beſt to be traytors too; ſo
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93777:23"/>he was as ſevere, as if <hi>I</hi> had been a traytor; yet he ſpake me very fair to my face, but <hi>I</hi> ſaw he indeavoured to catch my words, and to enſnare me, putting his own ſenſe upon them, but the Lord kept me out of his inſnarements, but he watched for my halting, and when my friends came a great way to ſee me, they had much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do to get into the Fort, and then my Gaoler ſat by, and heard what <hi>I</hi> ſaid to my friends, but this ſeverity was not many days, for Major <hi>Sanders</hi> came, and then my Gaoler departed, who told me the order did not make mention of my going to the Counſel, but Major <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> read that I ſhould, and ſo did the Lieutenant, but my Gao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler it may be had a mind to affright me, but he could not; and he told me I dreamed that the order run ſo; I am ſure I ſaid, I was not aſleep, but he jeered me, and he told Major <hi>Sanders,</hi> that I would not have ſo many people come to me: indeed he would have had no body come, if he could have bore ſway, but the Lord ordered all for my good: and when Major <hi>Sanders</hi> came, he gave me leave with a keeper, which was a friend, to go to hear the firſt dayes; and he was very courteous, and ſo was Lieutenant <hi>Lark,</hi> who came home with his wife before I was gone: I ſtayed there for the wind, and a States Ship to carry me: I ſtaid five weeks; the Lord made it but as a few dayes to me, I had ſo much of his preſence and power from him, he made kindneſſe flow from ſtrangers in the Family, and in the Fort; theſe were ſtrangers, and yet they were fellow Citizens, and I bleſſe the Lord, they are not now ſtrangers, but acquaintance, and they are a company that are written in my heart, they and their Teacher; for they were not aſhamed of my Chain, they owned me in my Bonds, and were a ſuccour to me in a ſtrange Countrey: my Soul was adminiſtred to by them, and the Paſtor over them; they every way adminiſtred to my neceſſity in what <hi>I</hi> ſtood in need of; I wanted not their help, and the people of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſhewed me love in viſiting me, and ſome of them when they had heard me pray, and in ſinging, they wept that they had taken up hard thoughts of me.</p>
               <p>Their Teacher Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> was very bitter againſt me, and would not come and talk with me, though ſome of his Auditory deſired him; but he writ to one of his friends at <hi>Cornwall,</hi> that he had read my book, and he from that drew that I was an impoſtor and he called the book non ſenſe, ſo that he confirmed his friend in her judging of me; and ſo he continued judging me for the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93777:24"/>ſake of that Diſpenſation he never ſaw, nor came not to try it by the word, but he indeavoured to incenſe others againſt me, and his ſometimes Scholler <hi>(R.V.)</hi> was afraid to diſpleaſe his Father <hi>Hughes,</hi> elſe he would have come according to his promiſe, but it may be had forgot that he promiſed a young man whom <hi>I</hi> ſent the firſt night <hi>I</hi> came, to tell him <hi>I</hi> was come to the Fort a priſoner and I knew not how little a while I ſhould ſtay; therefore I ſhould be glad to ſee him: and he told the Meſſenger that he would come next day, but he came not; and yet was much in the Town moſt part of my ſtay there, and many wondered he came not to ſee me, having been acquainted with me above ſeven years, the which they underſtanding, ſaid ſure, he knew ſome evil by me: thus it bred a jealouſie among ſtrangers, concerning me, but ſome ſaid, he would not ſuffer evil to be ſpoken of me; for he ſaid, ſure, the root of the matter was in me; he was much urged by my friends to come, but would not ſee me, though in bonds; and this uſe I was taught by the Lord, to make of that unkindneſſe of a friend, who I hearing, when I was coming to <hi>Plimouth,</hi> that ſuch an one was come there, I leaned upon him as a prop to me in my ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and I rejoyced much, ſaying to my friends, that he would vindicate me, who had been known to him ſo long, and one whom I was alwayes ready to vindicate, when aſperſed; but my God learned me to know, that all fleſh was graſſe, and a ſading flower, and like an <hi>Egyptian</hi> reed: and by this unkindneſſe from a friend, my God drew me the more to reſt upon himſelf alone; and what unkindneſſe I relate from any received, my end hereby is not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach or ſeek revenge on any, but the Lord my God knows, had there not been ſo many ſeverall reports paſſed far and near, I would not have ſet pen to paper in this kind, but it is that truth may ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence falſity; and though I fail in an orderly penning down theſe things, yet not in a true Relation, of as much as I remember, and what is expedient to be written; I could not have related ſo much from the ſhallow memory I have naturally, but through often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating theſe things, they become as a written book, ſpread open before me, and after which I write.</p>
               <p>Now I ſhall come again to the Relation, and tell you that I had much kindneſſe at <hi>Plimouth,</hi> from many, and great labour of love ſtewed me untill my departure, and ſome went with me a ſhipboard, and were ſory to have me go from their Quarters, not
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93777:24"/>that I was any thing, but the Lord did their ſouls good through a worm; and when we had been a day and a night toſſing on the Sea, the wind being againſt us, drove us back into the Harbour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: Some at <hi>Dartmouth</hi> reported that I had bewitched the winds, that the ſhips could not go to ſea, and they curſed me there, but the Lord bleſſed me the more; many reproaches he helpt me to bear, and though we were beating on the waves againſt the wind, yet I was not ſick; for the Lord had there much for me to declare to Sea men of free grace, and of the vileneſſe of mans nature, and the excellent work of Redemption. And I ſpake this unto them, and prayed and ſang in the Cabbin where I lay; and the Sea-men were much affected: the Lord made ſome of them declare how the Lord refreſhed them, and that they knew if I had ſtayed longer, much good their ſouls would have reaped, they were very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectfull to me, though there were few that had any relliſh of good, the Lord made much to be relliſhed by them, through a poore nothing creature: the Scripture the Lord inlarged amongſt them, in the 73. Pſalm, verſe 1. <hi>Truly, God is good to</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and to them that are of a clean heart;</hi> the new Covenant the Lord made known amongſt them very much; ſo that it was a bleſſed paſſage, though as from man it was bitter to be toſſed upon the Sea four dayes, and the maid that came with me, lying vomiting grievouſly by me, and ſick, even ready to dy, ſhe thought her heart would have broke, and I hurt my leg againſt the ſhip ſide, that it raged greatly a day and a night; and lying in a little Cabbin ſweating much, the maid and I together, which lodge was very little, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Maſters Cabbin, which was a little Lodge: But though I met with much difficulty, as to fleſh and blood, yet I murmured not, onely I was once a little troubled, and ſaid, Lord, why is man thus cruell to deal thus with me? they never conſidered whether my nature could bear the Sea: but I ſaid, Father, lay not this evil uſage to their charge. I was brought up among the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, that had robbed upon the Sea, and were taken priſoners, and ſent in the ſhip with me, but the Lord preſerved me from all hurt, and caried me ſafe to Land, and all in the ſhip; both Captain and Maſter, and men gave me civill reſpect while I was with them: So the Lord made good his promiſe to me, that nothing ſhould harm me, neither on the Sea, nor the Land.</p>
               <p>And the Captain with ſome of his men, came with me aſhore,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93777:25"/>and we landed at <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and the Governour not being in Town, <hi>I</hi> went with the Captain to Major <hi>Morefords,</hi> the deputy Governour, who receiving the order from the Captain of the ſhip, after ſome Diſcourſe with him he departed; and the Deputy Governour told me, <hi>I</hi> was committed to his Charge, untill ſuch time that he could diſpoſe of me with conveniency: ſo he lovingly entertained me, and thoſe two friends that came with me, and his daughters ſhewed me much kindneſſe: and in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon the Deputy Governour having no lodging in his houſe for me, he procured me lodging at Enſign <hi>Bakers,</hi> in the Town, and he went with me thither, it being not far off; and there he left me, deſiring the Enſigns wife to be kind to me, but ſhe heard <hi>I</hi> was a frenzy-headed creature, and ſhe looked very ſowr upon me, and all the while I was there, ſhe offered me no drink, nor any thing elſe; but one day when the Governour ſent his ſervant to ſee what I had, then ſhe ſent to me, and I had newly eaten a piece of Pye, that <hi>I</hi> had brought with me from <hi>Plimmouth,</hi> ſo that was all my food I eat from the ſecond day to the fifth day, that <hi>I</hi> came away; then ſhe ſeemed to be very kind, and ſaid, ſhe heard ſuch a clamour concerning me, which made her afraid of me, but after ſhe heard me, ſhe was of another mind. I prayed and ſang there a night and a day for the moſt part, and ſo departed from thence the next morning after, and came in a Coach to <hi>London,</hi> and a Lieutenant came with me to convey me to <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> and he brought a Preſent of Egges that was ſent from <hi>Gernſie</hi> to the great man at <hi>White Hall,</hi> they were Partridge Egges of the largeſt kind, <hi>I</hi> was told; and if they were not well put up, they could not be kept whole, for the Coach broke twice by the way, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturned once: it was a great mercy that we had no hurt, the dealings of man being unjuſt, every thing will make them mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and diſcover their breakings, where they or their Preſents be: If ſuch that hold forth King Jeſus be near, one danger or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will be lyable to meet withall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> was through Divine Power brought ſafe in the Coatch to <hi>Fox Hall,</hi> where we lighted, and the Coach man and Lieutenant told me, I muſt bear all my Charges, both by the way and the Coach hire, ſo <hi>I</hi> did, and <hi>I</hi> was brought from <hi>Fox Hall</hi> by water, to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and ſtayed a while at the <hi>George</hi> in Kings-ſtreet, and then, one of the Meſſengers came, and carryed me in a Coach to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93777:25"/>
                  <hi>Titons,</hi> but my friends payed the Coach hire; and at <hi>Titons</hi> houſe in <hi>Coven Garden,</hi> there that Meſſenger left me, which brought me thither; it was that Meſſenger that took hold of <hi>Vavaſor Powel,</hi> and carried him before the Councell, I told him it was no good office to be ſo imployed to lay hold of the Saints in that kind, but I ſaid, though I was troubled at him for his taking Mr. <hi>Powell,</hi> yet for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king me, and conducting me into cuſtody, I was no whit troubled at him, but I told him his Office was not good, this <hi>I</hi> ſaid, as I was riding to <hi>Titons;</hi> and there I was had to my Chamber, which was Mr. <hi>Feaks</hi> priſon firſt, ſo that I was quickly raiſed in my Joy, in thinking of that prayer, which had been put up in that room, for the coming of King Jeſus to raign on the earth, and to throw down <hi>Babylon,</hi> for this did that dear ſervant of Chriſt cry earneſtly, and the Lord made an unworthy handmaid to ſecond thoſe cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and to ring a peal to <hi>Whitehall</hi> ward, but they had not a mind to hearken, though the cry of a ſtone was brought near them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, occaſioned by their own doings, thinking to ſilence <hi>allelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jahs</hi>-triumphing over the beaſt, and the falſe Prophet, but they could not do it. The ſecret voyce of thunder hath a louder re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, than mens great Cannons. The Lord renewed my joy much at the ſight of my friends, and in the thoughts that I was brought, near <hi>Whitehall</hi> to be a witneſſe againſt their black doings, the which I hope I ſhall witneſſe againſt unto the death: that time at <hi>Tytons</hi> was ſpent much in prayer, and ſinging forth <hi>Babylons</hi> fall, and the ruine of thoſe which endeavoured to be nurſes and rockers to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylons</hi> brats; the Lord will cut off thoſe breaſts that give <hi>Babylon</hi> milk; for the whore of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Lord will not have nouriſhed by any, high or low, rich or poor, much was ſung to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe at <hi>Titons;</hi> and I often told of a preſent from heaven, which was much better than the preſent of <hi>Partridge</hi> egges; yea, it was coſtlier than the gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> or Rubies and Pearls from a far Countrey. I would fain have had the great Councel, and their Protectour, to have received a Preſent ſent from the great Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour, which is indeed, a Protectour of the faithfull, who makes uſe of ſilly handmaids to carry his preſent ſometimes; and I ſaid this, O great ones of the earth, is the Preſent from the great Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah to you? even his ſon Chriſt; in that you profeſſe your ſelves to be builders, the great God hath preſented to you a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93777:26"/>ſtone elect and precious, a ſure foundation, an excellent platform for thoſe that are willing to build to purpoſe; now therefore ſaid I unto you, that love rarities for Preſents, here are rarities indeed, not like thoſe things that will fade in their beauty, nor like that which ſoon loſeth its ſeent, though never ſo well perſumed, nor like that which in time will be waſted and gone, nor like Egges that are ſubject to rot or to break before they come to belarge Partridges, or any at all; but it was ſaid, oh that Protectour, and his Conncel, and Clergy, would all agree to receive ſuch a Preſent that fades not, nor cannot waſt, nor be broken, nor rot, nor is not ſubject to any caſualty; And for preſenting them with the Lords preſent, they ſent their meſſengers with a <hi>Bridewell</hi> reward to me, for all my pains and good will, and love to their welfare.</p>
               <p>I was eight dayes at <hi>Tytons</hi> houſe, expecting to be ſent for before the Council every day, according to their Orders, declaring that <hi>I</hi> was to come before them; but they had no time to hear the truth, from ſuch a ſilly nothing creature; and they ſent an Order ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with Preſident <hi>Laurences</hi> hand to it, which was brought by two meſſengers late at night, unto which I have already ſpoken ſomething off; the hour they came for me, and of their lothneſs to ſhow me the order, for my removal, but they did ſhew it me before my departure from thence.</p>
               <p>And now I am further to tell you, how I fared at my laſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which was in <hi>Bridewell,</hi> unto which I was brought at 11 of the clock in the Night, the Matron received me off the Meſſengers, And being brought by the Meſſengers of the Councell; ſhe thought I was ſome exceeding guilty perſon; and her words declared as much, for ſhe ſaid, I warrant you are one of the plotters? Its my portion ſaid I, to be dealt ſo with, as if I were one of them, but I am ſure that I am none; then the ſaid, I don't think but I have had in my keeping ſuch as you are before now; then ſhe lookt ſted faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in my face: And asked me, whether I did not know one Miſtris <hi>Cook,</hi> I ſaid, I had heard of ſuch a one, but I had no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of her: I warrant you are one of that crew ſhe ſaid; there is a company of ranting Sluts of which I have had ſome in my houſe, who have ſpoken a great many good words like you; but they had baſe actions: This diſcourſe paſt from her, and much more that night. And I ſaid to her, It no hurt to me to be ranked among
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93777:26"/>ſuch vile ones, which ſhe likened me to; but I bleſſe the Lord, ſaid I, that I am no ſuch, but do abhor ſuch evill practiſes; much was ſpoke while we waited for my freinds comming, whom I had ſent, for to take care for the Maid, that came out of <hi>Cornwall</hi> with me, the Matrons was loath to have fit up till my friends came, for it was almoſt twelve a clock at night; but at laſt my friends came, who ſaid; this our ſiſter is no vagabond, its well known by many in the City, her civill manner of life from a child, though the Counſell is pleaſed to deal thus with her, to ſend her to ſuch a place, among harlots and thieves; much to this purpoſe they ſpoke that night: and they deſired to ſee my Lodging, ſo ſhe had me up ſtairs into a large room, but it was very cloſe, there being but a little window at one corner of the room, and the Common ſhore running under the Window-place, which fink ſmelt grievouſly, and there was ſuch a filthy ſmell with the Rots that abode much in that room, ſo that at the firſt coming in, theſe ſcents entered much into my nice ſtomack, and having been newly ſetcht out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey too, and my friends that lived there hard by, were not able to endure the ſcent of the room, without ſtopping their noſtrils, but they ſaid nothing to me that night of what offended them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not diſcourage me: ſo the bed was made for me, which was a hard, flock-bed, and my friends ſaw it, and were much grieved to ſee my hard uſage, but they ſaw it was in vain to find fault that night: ſo they departed, and I was left alone. The Matron would not admit of the maids being with me, who came from <hi>Cornwall</hi> with me, but ſaid, ſhe would tend me, I ſhould not have a maid to wait on me there: ſo my friends departed from me, leaving me in the Lords protection, and the Matron bid me make haſt to bed, for ſhe muſt fetch away the candle, for ſhe ſaid, ſhe did not truſt her priſoners to put it out,</p>
               <p>And when ſhe was gone down, as I was making my ſelf unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, I was much aſſaulted by Satan and my own heart; who ſaid, to be ſo forward for God, ſee what thou haſt got by it, thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther little thought this would have befallen thee, when ſhe prayed that God would double his ſpirit on thee, now thou mayeſt ſee what her prayer is come to; I then was tempted to murmure at that prayer, and the Tempter bid me ſpeak againſt that prayer, and the Tempter ſaid to me, that I ſhould be a by-word and a laughing-ſtock while I lived, and that every one would point at me as I went
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93777:27"/>up &amp; down the ſtreets, when I came out, they would ſay, there goes a <hi>Bridwell</hi> bird, and then many will gather about thee, to mock and deride thee; and as for thy kindred, they will be aſhamed of thee, and will not care to hear thy name mentioned in their ears, becauſe of <hi>Bridewell</hi> reproach, and therefore ſaid Satan wilt thou ſtill retain thy faith concerning Chriſt as King and Governour in the Earth; And I was tempted to let go my confidence as to this, but my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kept me, and gave me a diſcovery of my Saviour, as he was hung between two thieves, and alſo brought thoſe ſcriptures to my thoughts which makes a report of Chriſt, as he was ranked among tranſgreſſours; and how he that knew no ſin was dealt with, ſo as to indure the contradiction of finners.</p>
               <p>And now the Lord talked with me about my Saviours ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering much for me, and therefore do not hearken to Satan ſaid the Lord, but look unto him that ſuffered the contradiction of ſinners for thy ſake, then was my heart cheared, and I went unto the unlovely lodging, and the Matron locked me in, or bolted me in, I know not well which, but there I was ſhut in alone, and yet not alone, for Chriſt was with me; and when I had lain a while, I grew very ſick, for the hard damp bed ſtruck much into my ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and the cold ſheets; ſo that all this ſet me into an Ague, and I ſhook much, and my limbs ſmarted with cold, and I ſmelt ſuch a ſtrong ſcent about the bed, that my heart panted, and lay beating, and my ſtomack working, and my head aching exceeding much, moſt part of my being in that Lodge this firſt night; and at break of the day, I threw off the cloaths from my ſtomach, for I was almoſt ſpent, being very fick, and in much pain ſome hours: and I ſaid, dear Father, haſt thou brought me to <hi>Bridewell</hi> to dye; the Lord and my Father anſwered me preſently, and ſaid no; thou ſhalt not dye but live, and declare the works of the Lord; and he further told me, that though my heart and my ſtrength failed me, the Lord was the ſtrength of my heart, and my portion for ever, and he would never leave me nor forſake me; the Lord ſaid, he would be my ſafety from the horn of men and Devils; and I then recovered a little ſtrength, and I ſang forth allelujahs ſong of thankſgiving, and I out of that fell in a little ſlumber; and my friends came, and waked me preſently, againſt their wills they did it, for they were very tender of me, and it grieved them greatly,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93777:27"/>when they heard what a night I had; they then ſpake a while to me, and ſoon after I roſe, and made me ready, and then went to prayer with ſome of my ſiſters that came that morning, and after prayer I received much reviving in my outward man, but was not well, yet I walked about the houſe all that day, and was in the lower roome with my friends, who came that day many of them, whom I walk in fellowſhip with, and many others; for they thought I was put in a place that would daunt me, if the Lord did not much appear to me; and they came to expreſſe their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der love and care that they had of my welfare, and they pleaded very much with the Matron, and fetcht out the order that brought me there, and procured a Copy of it, which coſt them ſixteen pence, a few words copying out; and this Copy of the Order was ſhewed to the Matron, how that nothing was laid to my charge, and that I was onely to be kept there, till further order; and my friends prayed her to let me have another bed, and other Sheets, the which they offered me of theirs, but that ſhe would not grant, but they prevailed at length with her after much perſwaſion, to lay me on one of her beds, and to let me have other ſheets, the which I had the ſecond night, and they procured one to be with me, for they ſaid, I was not fit to be alone, for that I was oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times weak in body, and required help: ſo they alſo obtained, that, ſome ingaging to the Matron, that they would bear her harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in her giving way to this: many that day ſo ſweetned my Chamber with ſeverall perſumes, and ſtrowed it with herbs, and Flowers, that it much altered the ſmell, yet it ſmelled very offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive all the time of my being there, though I every day ſometimes was burning many ſeverall things in the room for the firſt week, and ſeverall times while I was there, and after this day, I was very ſick; yet the Matron urged me with the firſt day of the week to go hear their Miniſter at <hi>Bridewell,</hi> but I told her, I was very ill, ſhe ſaid, ſhe thought I diſſembled at the firſt, but afterward ſhe thought it was a Judgement from the Lord, my ſickneſſe, becauſe I was unwilling ſhe ſaid, to hear their Miniſter: and ſhe ſaid, ſhe ſaw by my high colour, that I was not well, and indeed I was much in a feaver that day onely, I had the ague a little while in a cold fit, and I lay, not deſiring to be ſpoke to, becauſe it was painfull for me to ſpeak, or to turn my ſelf in my bed: and the next day
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:93777:28"/>the ague and feaver was much upon me, ſo that my heart even ſunk within me, I being ſo burning and in ſo cloſe a room, and friends had a great ado to get to ſee me, the Matron was ſo ſtrict, and would hardly let them in, but ſome friends came, who made me plaiſters to lay to my wriſts, and poſſet drink, to drink the next fit.</p>
               <p>But that ſecond day in the night, I was pleading with the Lord, and asked of the Lord a removall of that ſicknes, and ſaying, Lord, its very grievous to ly ſick in this place; the Lord anſwered me, and ſaid, I have taken away thy ſickneſſe, thou ſhalt be ſick no more, while thou art here thou art here in <hi>Bridewell,</hi> for I will fill thee with more triumph here, than ever thou hadſt in thy life, ſo the Lord did I am ſure; and it was further ſaid to me, thy friends have provided means to take away thy Ague, but the Lord hath been thy Phyſician aforehand; and he further ſaid, he would take me into the mount that day, for the perfect cure of my ſickneſſe, and ſo the Lord did, and I ſpake by way of prayer and ſinging from morning till night, and felt no fickneſſe nor pain, nor faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not all that day, nor at night when I came to my ſelf, to be capable of a body; for truly, all that day I was wrapt up, ſo that I could not tell, whether I was in the body or out: and yet I ſung with underſtanding, as to the things the Lord was do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among the ſonnes and daughters of men; and at ninght, I had ſweet reſt all night, and in the morning, it being the fourth day the Matron came and told me, that it was a Court day, and I muſt riſe and go to the Court, I have been ſick I ſaid, and I prayed her to tell them ſo; ſhe came the ſecond time, and bid me riſe to go before the Court, I told her I was weak, and had lain in my bed three dayes, onely I roſe the ſecond day, and could hardly indure up while my bed was made, and I thought it not ſafe to riſe up, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I was in a ſweat, &amp; go preſently into the aire; ſhe came the third time, and ſaid, if you will not riſe, I muſt ſend the man to call you up, that was an old man, that called up the harlots and thieves, every morning betimes to beat hemp, he was to ſlap them up to work; and ſhe threatned to ſend him to fetch me up, but I ſaid, tell the Court I have been ſick, and am not fit to riſe out of the bed; but many of my friends came who perſwaded me to ſtrive to riſe and go to the Court, ſo I did, my ſiſter <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula Adman,</hi> help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:93777:28"/>me, and other of my ſiſters, and they led me up to the Court, for I was very weak, ſo that the Court gave me leave to ſit down before them, they were very courteous to me, and they ſpoke not much to me, onely ſaid, it was the Cuſtome they had to ſee all their priſoners at their firſt coming in; I told them, truly, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, I would have waited on you ſooner, but I have been ſick and therefore I ſtayed ſo long before I came before you, there was through ſome words ſpoken an opportunity given me to tell them of my ſickneſſe, the Matron finding fault with ſo many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple coming to ſee me, I told them, that if I had not been put into ſuch a place, it was probable ſo many would not have come; but further I ſaid to them, I being put into ſuch a cloſe room, coming out of the freſh air it was very offenſive to me, the room and the bed had ſuch a ſtrong ſcent, and damp, that it ſet me into an ague, and a Feavor; one of them ſaid, they did not uſe to have their beds ſmell where their priſoners lay, for they were lookt well too; I ſaid, but the ſcent was grievous to me, and the bed was damp ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not been laid upon, not lately it may be; I ſaid truly Sir, if you had been there, you might have ſmelt it, the ſcent was very grievous to me and others who ſmelt it as well as I; I am ſure, I told them it was a cauſe of my ſickneſſ; for I was well when I came there: Then the Matron ſaid, I ſpoke to wrong her, but I did not: onely I would have it known what was the reaſon of my ſickneſſe. I am certain I had no revenge any way towards her, then ſhe told them that I would have men come to me, and that word went to my heart, I knowing my baſhfull nature, and my civill life was known to many; and I ſaid to them truly, Gentlemen, my delight is not nor never was in mens company, but in all people as they are godly, I delight in their company: And I ſaid, that the Officers of the Church was to look after the members of the Church, they ſaid it was reaſon they ſhould, and they were not againſt it: They as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked me how many was of them Officers, I ſaid about ten I thought: they asked me how many I would have come to ſee me of my ſiſters at a time, I ſaid, 6. ſo it was granted; but ſome would have had their names penned down, that ſo onely thoſe half a doozen might have come; but it was procured otherwayes by friends. And after this the Lord gave health and ſtrength and ſtomack to my food, and a better digeſtion then ever I had ſince I can remember.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:93777:29"/>
               <p>The Lord alſo filled me with joy unſpeakable, and full of glory in believing, and many viſions and Hallelujah ſongs I had there; and more frequent they were then they ever had been: I was at <hi>Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> Court, once more only to be gated on; for little was ſaid to me, onely they asked me, why I lay there ſtill; And I ſaid, I waited upon the pleaſure of the Councel: And they asked me, why my friends did not ſeek to get my liberty? I ſaid, I know not, they know what they have beſt to do themſelves; one ſaid, but they come every day to ſee you, do not they tell you what they will do? I ſaid, I do not ask them, I leave it to them; Something more was ſaid, and I came away, and retired to my Chamber, where in I kept moſt of thoſe eight weeks, paying five ſhillings a week for it; It coſt forty ſhillings, and I bleſſe the Lord that I had friends, and ſome means of my own, elſe I muſt have lain in the Goale upon ſtraw: The Matron told me, ſo the firſt night, and when ſome ſaid, If I muſt beat Hemp, they would beat for me; She ſaid, I ſhould beat it my ſelf: and for ought ſhe knew I was to beat Hemp, but ſhe did not know me; and ſo ſpoke as ſhe uſed to ſpeak to thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve harſhneſſe; for after ſhe had knowledge of me, ſhe was very loving, and reſpectfull both to me, and to my Siſter <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula Adman,</hi> who kept me company ſeven weeks of my being there: She was a friend born for the day of adverſity, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks; and indeed ſhe, night and day, ſhewed her tenderneſſe to me, and helped to bear my burden. And therein ſhe fulfilled the law of Chriſt, and ſhe did this as a freewill Offering, love conſtraining her thereunto, ſo that it was thereby made eaſie to her to bear and indure that which few would, eſpecially ſo freely without reward; yet I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent the Lord will reward her double for that priſon kindneſs, ſhe let out to me without any fainting, or being troubled, that the time was long, or the noiſes burdenſome; there was many diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties to undergo night and day; but little quiet ſleep to be had, there was ſuch ſcoulding among the priſoners neer our lodging: and they were brought in often a nights which made a great noiſe, and the Rats run about our bed, and made a great noiſe, like dogs and Cats in the Room; and this was no pleaſant priſon ſure to ſuch that were brought up tenderly, and never knew any hardſhip as to the outward man: And truly the Lord made this and many more anoiances, received in <hi>Bridwell</hi> priſon, to be very pleaſantly
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:93777:29"/>imbraced by divine love appearing in the midſt of all trials; my God made this ſmarting ſcourge (as from man it was ſo) but God I ſay made it eaſie; for his tenderneſſe was much, he made foes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come friends, and the harſh to be kind, and overcame the rough and haſty ſpirits; the Lord is worthy of all praiſe. I had but a little while affliction in my ſpirits, which was occaſioned by a friend, and that made it grievous, but the Lord made that little ſtorm, to work abundance of good to me many ways: and all things that were afflictive, the Lord quickly broke ſuch ſetters. I ſaid not, O when will there be an end of this or the other affliction, but I often ſaid, and deſired a purging out of my corruptions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a removall of ſufferings, that ſo I might come out more holy and more humble, and more ſelfe-denying and ſelfe-debaſing, and abhorring them when I went into priſon: That ſo I might all my dayes be willing to take up the Croſſe of Chriſt, and follow him, whether ſo ever he would have me, either to do or ſuffer: I ſhall begin to ſhorten my relation, leaſt I ſhould be too tedious to the Reader, and leave the Viſions and opening of Scriptures, that the Lord brought to my ſoul, while I was in <hi>Bridwell</hi> for my own benefit, and for others that are his little flock, with whom he hath made an everlaſting Covenant, well ordered in all things and ſure.</p>
               <p>At the time neer my comming out, ſome came and defired me to Petition, I told them I had not offended man, whereby to ſeek to him; And they knew that I was in Priſon by their order; but ſome ſaid they may forget: I ſaid, that they could not, for many of their friends ſtill told them: The Protector ſaid, he did not know that I was put in <hi>Bridewell,</hi> till I had been there above a week, that one went and informed him: but it was a ſtrange thing that ſervants ſhould do ſuch an Act without their Maſter, and great Governours knowledge; ſurely, if he had not liked of it, he would have reproved them: but ſaid I, now he knows it, and yet he doth not ſend for me out. Again, ſome others came and ſaid, they knew they could quickly procure my Liberty: I told them, I would not come out upon baſe terms: ſaid one to me, what are your terms, let us hear them? I ſaid, they ſhall acknowledge the reproach and odium they have brought upon me, through this their priſon: ſaid one, is that your terms? then you mayly long
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93777:30"/>enough; but ſurely all rational men will ſay, this was but equity: Then after this, ſome ſpoke great matters, what they would do for my liberty: and they went to the Counſell and ſpoke to them, and Preſident <hi>Laurence,</hi> ſaid, if that I would, or any for me ingage, I might come out; but ſaid Captain <hi>Kettlebeator,</hi> none can ingage, for ſhe her ſelf cannot ingage as to a diſpenſation, that ſhe is ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up in, that ſhe knows not what is done about her at that time, nor capable of any being with her in the room: And he told him, that he had known me many years: And my whole deportment of life had been, and was very civill and religious; he ſpake more to that purpoſe: Aud the Preſident ſaid, ſo he had underſtood; ſome more ſpeech they had, and they came to tell me that, nay what they had ſpoke in my behalf: I ſaid, I will never ingage to that which lies not in me to perform, for what the Lord utters in me, I muſt ſpeak: ſo one ſaid, he would go again to the Counſell, I told him I deſired no favour of them but juſtice and equity: and if he could procure my comming before them to hear what they have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, thats all I deſire of you I ſaid; and what he ſaid or did, it was of his own offering: ſo he ſaid, he would not leave them ſo, but he would go again and try what they would do; but I heard no more concerning him, he was forgetfull it may be, like his Maſter: After this ſome others undertook this buſineſſe, and came to hear what I would ſay to it. And one asked me upon what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I ſuffered impriſonment, whether it was for Chriſt, and if ſo then I had a great deal of comfort in my ſufferings, for he ſaid, he had found it ſo, having been impriſoned for the teſtimony of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; I told him the Councel never ſent for me, to tell me upon what account they impriſon me here for; and I ſaid, the recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zances are taken off concerning <hi>Cornwall</hi> buſineſſe, ſo that I was meerly upon the pleaſure and wills of the Councel, and of Lord <hi>Laurance;</hi> for indeed I will call him my <hi>Bridewell</hi> Lord, for that his hand was in chief to the Order: but I told them, I was ſure I ſuffered for Chriſt. And I enjoyed his preſence abundantly; and I gave them ſome account of my ſufferings, and of the Lords comforts therein, then after ſome further diſcourſe, they asked me whether, I would be willing to go out, if an Order ſhould come for my liberty? I told them, I would never ingage: they ſaid, that was not deſired; I ſaid, yes but it was, for my Lord <hi>Laurence</hi> told ſome if I would ingage, I might come out: then they ſaid, but if
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:93777:30"/>the Order come, and give you liberty freely, will you accept of it? I was ſilent, onely my ſiſter ſaid, if we can have liberty, we will chuſe it rather than bonds? ſo after a little while theſe departed.</p>
               <p>And the next week after, upon the ſixth day of the week, I roſe early in the morning and walked about my Chamber, putting up requeſts to the Lord ſecretly for purging grace, that I might go out of priſon much more purified from the droſſe of corruptions, then when I went into priſon fire; that ſo others might ſee it had been a purifying furnace to me: And after I had been up ſome hours, I ſaid to my ſiſter that abode with me, I think ſaid I to her, every one that I hear coming to the door, comes from the Councel with an Order for my liberty; come let us pray before it comes, and ask councell of God concerning it, and the Lord indeed counſelled me, and took me into the mount of heavenly rapture that day, ſo that my friends were fain to take we off my knees and lay me upon my bed, where I lay praying and ſinging more then every I did in my life unto many publick concernments, the which I am ſure will be accompliſh'd in due time: and I often deſired that they in high places had ſome of the dainties with me at <hi>Bridewell;</hi> and that day the Order was brought, and I lay ſilent when they came with it; but I was talking with the Lord who ſhewed me many things, which I know ſhall come to paſſe, and the Lord told me that my freedome out of that place was neer, the which I ſaw three weeks before, and ſang it forth, ſo I did now; one of them tarried that brought the Order, I was told ſo afterwards; but I knew not that any was by me, when I thus lay, either ſilent or ſpeaking. That day I ſpake to ſome that ſaid, he would chuſe impriſonment for gain, he ſpoke of an outward gain, but if he got by his impriſonment formerly; I am ſure I cannot ſay, nor thoſe that are impriſoned upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for the fifth Monarchy, cannot ſay ſo: we would not gain for our outward man, if we might, by robbing others, to enrich our ſelves; I can ſay, I have refuſed what hath been tendered me freely: I took nothing ſave for my neceſſity, unto which I had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſupply, had not the Rulers put me to ſuch charges through their impriſonment, and bringing me from place to place, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king me pay for it. So that I have been robbed, but I have robbed none: I had rather go in a Canvaſs Coar, or any mean garb, then ſo do; and eat any mean kind of food, then to fair dainty and go in brave robes with that coſt, which is others right in heritance.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:93777:31"/>
               <p>I ſhall further relate in the cloſe of this relation, how the next day I came ſorth, for I came not into a capable frame, to ſpeak to any body, till late at night, on the ſixth day; and when I ſpoke that night, my friends ſaid, do you know you are ſet at liberty? you ſang as if you had known; I ſaid, the Lord hath given it me, I will thank him for it; ſo you told us to day in your finging, ſaid my friends: And the next morning the Keeper of <hi>Bridewell</hi> came, and ſaid, <hi>I</hi> was free by order from the Councel, and <hi>I</hi> might go out when <hi>I</hi> pleaſed: <hi>I</hi> told him they ſhould fetch me out that put me in; had they put me among Thieves and Whores, and now did they ſend for me out without acknowledging the reproach they had brought upon me? He ſaid, the ſame Order with the ſame hands that puts you in fetches you out: <hi>I</hi> deſired to ſee my Order, ſo <hi>I</hi> ſhould he ſaid, if <hi>I</hi> would pay ſixteen pence for a Copy of it: ſo <hi>I</hi> ſent for it, and read it. And ſeeing <hi>I</hi> might go out upon no diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable terms, and the Lord having inſtructed me before hand, he being my guide and Counſeller, in my impriſonment, and in my comming out. And <hi>I</hi> ſaid to a friend, go tell your Maſters, though they will not ſee me they ſhall be ſure to hear from me, and ſo they have: for <hi>I</hi> ſent letters to them, that ſo they might not ſay, they had not heard of the injuſtice acted under their dominion: Now <hi>I</hi> have given a Declaration, through the aſſiſtance of the Lord, and not to ſet up my ſelf and throw down others; but to throw down lies, and exalt truth; the Lord would not have Cities nor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, nor <hi>White-hall</hi> Councel, a refuge for lies: For his people are recorded in the 63 of <hi>Iſa. v.</hi> 8. to be children that will not lie, ſo he became their Saviour: <hi>I</hi> deſire that truth may be written in Buſſe and ſent through <hi>Europe; I</hi> would have the whole world taſt the ſweetnes of truth, that all people may know, and ſee, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and underſtand together, the hand of the Lord, and what he is doing, and will do for his, that truſt in him; And ſure wiſdom is juſtified of her children: Come, O you children of wiſdom, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that you may underſtand, and ſeek after Chriſts raign, and ſay with me. <hi>Come Lord Jeſus come quickly, according to thy ſaying, Even ſo come Lord Jeſus;</hi> Let thoſe that waite on the Lords comming ſay, <hi>Amen, even ſo be it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:93777:31"/>
            <head>A Defiance to all reproachfull, ſcandalous, baſe, horrid, defaming ſpeeches, which have been vented by Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Clergy, and their Auditors, and publiſhed in ſcurrilous Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets up and down in Cities and Countries, againſt <hi>Anna Trapnell,</hi> late Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in <hi>Bridwell</hi> for the Teſtimony of Jeſus the Lord.</head>
            <p>I Am forc't out of my cſoſe retired ſpirit, by Rulers and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, who have brought me upon the worlds ſtage of Reports, and Rumors, making me the worlds wonder, and gazing ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>: and as ſome have ſaid they thought I had been a Monſter or ſome ill-ſhaped Creature, before they came and ſaw, who then ſaid, they muſt change their thoughts, for I was a woman like others that were modeſt and civill, and many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending words they uttered; which (becauſe its of my own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forbear to mention; and what I do mention is to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance free grace ſhewed me, in making gain-ſayers to receive a check in their own conſciences, and to be aſhamed that they took up reports: Truly Rulers &amp; Clergy, I wii bid Defiance to all the words &amp; actions which have undeſervedly and unjuſtly been by you or others vented againſt, and inflicted upon me; I ſpeak this (the Lord my my God knowes) not vauntingly, but humbly: For I am conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to my ſelf, that I have abundance of infirmities, and am ſure the worſt of all the Lord's Flock, indeed a ſorry worthleſs creature; and as from the Lord I deſerve nothing ſave hell and eternall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, yet he loves me, and hath loved me with an everlaſting love; and will you, Oh men, condemn and paſſe your ſentences upon me?</p>
            <p>Firſt, for a Witch; Pray, wherein can you make this appear? Oh you Inhabitants of <hi>Fruroer,</hi> and Clergie there or in any other place, or at Court; Can any Ruler there make good their words? I am ſure, I may defie this their ſpeech, and will.</p>
            <p>Further, they call me Impoſtor; Pray which of the wayes and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:93777:32"/>Ordinances or Statutes of the Lord have I perverted through de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit? Canſt thou, Oh man, or woman, lay any thing of this nature to my Charge? Do then; but through grace you cannot: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I can defie this ſaying alſo.</p>
            <p>Again, you call me vagabond; but how will you make that good? All the Art, skill, or policy that any politician hath among you, cannot make this ſaying true, not in the leaſt: I lived with my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther till ſhee dyed, which was about twenty years, then I kept houſe with the means my Mother left me, and payed taxes towards maintaining of the Army then in the field; and this I did not grudgingly, but freely and willingly; I ſold my Plate and Rings, and gave the mony to the Publick uſe; you did not call me vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond then; I am compel'd, as I told you, to bring my private Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit forth to the view of the world, and to declare my free-will-of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, yet not boaſtingly, but ſo as that the world may judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this term of vagabond will hold good concerning me; the ſum of money my Mother left me, I freely gave for the Armies uſe, and I wrought many nights hard to get mony, the which I chearfully beſtowed, not on my own back nor belly chear, but fared hard, that ſo I might miniſter towards the relief of the Nation; and if that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle means which I have left had been in mony, I could not have kept it from you; Oh Army, and Rulers, that then would not have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed me; I pray why are you ſo unchriſtian like in your carriages to me now? you have taxes from me ſtill; and am I a vagabond for this? Ask your Lawyers, will they not ſay you were much to blame herein? Let all that knew me, ſpeak, when they ſaw or knew me a vagabond: After the time was over of my keeping houſe, I was deſired by Mrs. <hi>Spenſer,</hi> a Miniſters Widow, to abide with her, and her daughters, who were ſober, holy, humble walkers with God, and not of a frothy, wanton, light, giddie carriage and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, as many Profeſſors in thoſe dayes appeared in; I lived among theſe, taking up my abode with Mrs. <hi>Harlow,</hi> daughter to the aforementioned Mrs. <hi>Spenſer,</hi> who lived near her Mother in the <hi>Minneries;</hi> She, her maid, and I lived together a while, and they are my witneſſes, whether I was then idle, and others beſide them can witneſſe for me; I kept cloſe to the Word, and faſting, and Prayer, and ſo obſerving times for civill imployment; was I a vagabond then? Then I was deſired by Mrs. <hi>Wythe</hi> my kinſwoman, a Merchants wife in <hi>Fau-Church-ſtreet,</hi> to live with her, with whom
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93777:32"/>I lived ſix years; could I be a vagabond there? They ſhall be my judges in this, I lived with them in City and Country till Rulers were diſpleaſed at a diſpenſation above their underſtanding, and therefore gave out threatning ſpeeches, that my Relation and friend where I lived was afraid to receive me for loſing his Place: And now I have related my places of abode from my Childhood, untill the 11. month 1653. all which time I ſuppoſe no rationall man will ſay I was a vagabond: And as for the time ſince, as ſoon as I was rejected of my kinſman for the Rulers ſake, many friends would have let me into their houſes, which are very grave, godly, conſciencious, wiſe, ſober, perſons, that are unwilling to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain vagabonds; but to this day I have a ſettled habitation, and pay aſſeſſments, therefore ſtand convinced from this day, and hereafter all you Rulers, Clergie, and People in all Places and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, that I <hi>Anna Trapnell</hi> am no vagabond, nor Runagate Perſon, though I have and may ſometimes live in the City, and ſometimes in the Country, as your ſelves do, and why ſhould I be accounted a vagabond more then you?</p>
            <p>Let me yet further, bid defiance to thoſe that have called me Whore, which language hath proceeded from Court, I hear ſo; and will any that have ſaid ſo, ſtand to their words without bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? Truly, I would try them, were there any Law up, ſave the wils of men; you may peradventure ſay, this ſavours of revenge; I anſwer, It doth not, for <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Name of the righteous is as a precious Ointment,</hi> and therefore dead flyes are to be caſt out, which would putrifie it, and its to be carefully preſerved becauſe coſtly and precious for uſe, ſo that if it be putrified its not of uſe; ſo Chriſts flock are for his uſe, and he keepeth them, that nothing can putrifie them in that new-born State they are in; yet as to that uſefulneſſe for the benefit of Saints and ſinners, herein they may be hindered, through the dead flies ſtinking-ſent, brought on their Names, that all people may have no knowledge of: And as to this Charge, being I do not ſuffer as an evill doer, I will triumph and give glory to the Lord my God, who hath kept me from open prophaneneſſe, and from ſecret ſins, and in a great meaſure hath freed me from my iniquity, which is the ſin of my diſpoſition, which doth not run out, nor incline to luſtfulneſſe, neither of the fleſh nor eye, nor pride of life; but my iniquity is paſſion, apt to be haſtie, its more within than appears without; this I ſpeak to my ſhame,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:93777:33"/>and the advancement of free grace not ſo prompt any, or my ſelf to boaſt of ſinfull infirmities, though God heals my backſlidings, and loves me freely; I will not ſin that grace may abound, but I will confeſſe my ſins to him who is juſt and faithfull to forgive, and he that covers his ſin cannot proſper; it's written, he that ſaith he hath no ſin is a lyar; yet I can ſay, they are lyars that have thus reported of me, as I have penned down, and having this boldneſſe which is not of a carnall form, I may look my enemies in the face with chearfulneſſe, and yet with ſobriety, and ſo I can through mercy and Divine goodneſſe, and oh that all my Adverſaries would take the pains, as <hi>David</hi> did to finde out their iniquity, which dogs them at the heels, ſo that they may cry againſt it, and be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled before the Lord: I would fain be conformable to the death and reſurrection of Chriſt, though I fall ſhort, indeed I do, I am not unwilling to confeſſe it; yet oh, yet I can with a face unvailed contend with my adverſaries, whether they be men or devils, and bid defiance to them for Chriſts ſake: As for me, truly I am not worth mentioning, nor regarding by any, none can ſure think vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of me than I think of my ſelf: yet I bleſſe the Lord, and my Father, as unto mens reports I am not guilty, nor a tranſgreſſor in their ſenſe, for the which I praiſe Jehovah, and ſtill I will advance him who is my All in All.</p>
            <p>I have a further word with the <hi>Cornwell</hi> Jurors, who ſay they are for the Lord protector of the Commonwealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. and upon their Oaths preſent <hi>Anna Trapnell</hi> to be a dangerous ſeditious Perſon, not onely, ſay they, imagining, but deviſing and maliciouſly intending the peace, tranquillity and feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the good people of this Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb, but, ſay they, to move, ſtir up, and raiſe diſcord, rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and inſurrection among the good People of <hi>England,</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; this they affirmed upon oath, in their Indictment; all which I bid defiance to as falſe; &amp; likewiſe thoſe ſayings of theirs, W<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> were, that I would cauſe authorities, juſt and righteous Actions to be brought into contempt, diſgrace, and hated with the good People, calling me one of a devilliſh minde, and wicked imaginations; and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I uttered with a loud voice malicious, ſcandalous, horrible, and ſeditious words in the hearing of diverſe people: Can you tell what you ſay? Oh Jurors, when you ſay you are for the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, I am ſure you do not mean the great Lord Protector of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:93777:33"/>and earth, ſea, and dry land, who hath indeed all Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons belonging unto him: And as for him you call your Protector, you do not give him that tithe in love to him more than to another, nor ſo much as to old King <hi>Charles,</hi> and to his Son, who is in your hearts, you love a King dearly, Oh that you did love King Jeſus, he would never fail you, he would teach you to make your indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments truer, and not upon perſons undeſerving, he would teach you not to uſe his children as witches, and vagabonds when they come into your parts: I pity you, oh you envious Jurors you have not injured me, nor indicted me, but your ſelves, and though I could ſay, when before you examined, <hi>Not guilty,</hi> I could ſay ſo with a clear conſcience, yet I am ſure you can not ſay ſo, at the Lords judgement ſeat, when he ſhall read the Bill of Indictment againſt you, can you ſay to him, you are not of a divilliſh minde, nor of a wicked imagination, nor ſeditious, nor maliciouſly bent againſt the great Lord Protector and his ſubjects, againſt whom you ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, deviſe, ſtir up, and raiſe diſcord, rebellion and inſurrection againſt the great Lord Protector, and his good People aforeſaid, endeavouring to bring his righteous and juſt Actions into contempt diſgrace, and hatred amongſt all ſorts of People, good and bad, And be it known <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that the Jehovah Protector is my King, Prieſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Kingly power I obey, and all government conſonant to it, and whoſe Prieſthood, and alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that which ſhall offend it, and make it of no effect; and I love to liſten to that great Prophet, who teaches like him; and though I ſay thus, yet I love the Goſpel found in &amp; through the Lords Trumpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; I do not deſpiſe true Propheſie from any, I love to read what the Lord ſpake through a <hi>Balaam,</hi> who was a ſorcerer yet ſpoke excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently of Chriſt, that bleſſed ſtarre of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and Redeemer of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> This I ſpeak, to give you to underſtand my delight, and love to all the Lords Ordinances and ſpeakings; ſo that I muſt take leave to mention another defiance to your Letter you ſent againſt me to <hi>London,</hi> wherein you reported that I denied Ordinances, which hundereds of people can and will witneſſe to the contrary; Thus you may ſee your folly, Oh, you <hi>Cornwell Clergie,</hi> and Juſtices; and indeed I ſhould be glad, if you ſaw your evill, and repented, and humbled your ſouls before the Lord, againſt whom you have ſinned: what you have done to me is ſmall, when compared with your treſpaſſe againſt the living God, whoſe appearing is as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:93777:34"/>fire, and everlaſting burnings; who can dwell with God and ſtand before him, when he thus appeares? The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> tels you, 33.15. <hi>He that walketh righteouſly, and ſpeaketh uprightly, he that deſpiſeth the gain of oppreſſions, that ſhaketh his hands from hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of bribes, that ſtoppeth his ears from hearing of bloud, and ſhutteth his eyes from ſeeing evill, they ſhall dwell on high;</hi> their place of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſhall be not onely a Rock, but munitions of rocks, like the ſtrength of many Rocks, that are many times doubled, and treehed one within another, and one a top of another, which maketh it an high and a ſtrong place that none can enter, or reach the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right; the upright ſhall ſee him in his glory, which is a ſight worth the making after, and preparing for: Who will withhold no good thing from thoſe that love his appearing, he will give them ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for walls and bulwarks, as it is written, and he taketh them as he did <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he ſhewed him <hi>Canaan</hi> afar off, ſo the Lord will take all his faithfull ones, and ſhew them the lovely Land, wherein no Dragon can caſt his floods; nor wolf can catch the ſheep into their priſon-paws, nor Lyon can caſt into their <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi>-den; there ſhall be no Fox to Inform, and lay hold with their Souldiours, the Children and Saints of the moſt high God; this Land is a ſafe place, where no ravenous beaſt ſhall moleſt the Saints; and the Beauty of King Jeſus ſhall take ſo with them, that they ſhall forget all their hard meaſure, that they have had from the ſons and daughters of men. And then who ſhall be ſo ſo deep ſpeecht, as Saints now who are counted Novices, and ſhallow fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and frantique handmaids, not fit to ſtand to ſpeak to the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned wiſe Rabbies of theſe times, which call ſuch that ſpeak plainly phantick, and under the adminiſtration of evill Angels and ſeditious whimſicall headed ones; but the time is coming which will diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the King in his Beauty to his, that are ſo ſlighted, and then they ſhall be the onely Scribes who are the Lords choſen <hi>Baruchs,</hi> he will imploy them to write his Roules; and truly he now makes uſe of them, to meditate terrour, and to count the Towers; they are not deceived in their accounts, concerning the beaſt and the falſe Prophets, and thoſe that adhere to them, which ſhall feel the terrour of the Lord; and they, their Scribes, Receivers, and Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhall fall before him whoſe Name is a ſtrong Tower, into whom the righteous run and are ſafe, and therefore let not any wondes at thoſe that pleadeth praiſe for the Name of King Jeſus, which is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:93777:34"/>ſo blaſphemed, and ſet at naught by ſelf ſeekers; the Name of the Lord is worth ſuffering for, and they that have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffered for it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.24, 25, 26.</note> and do ſtill ſuffer for it, may joy in the Lord as their Portion, which the Church rejoyced in, though in great afflictions, that God was her Portion, and ſhe would hope in him, and ſaith, <hi>The Lord is good to thoſe that wait for him, and to the ſoul that ſeeketh him, its good,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>to hope, and quietly wait for the ſalvation of the Lord;</hi> they that hope aright to ſee the King in his beauty, they quietly wait, they wait without murmuring: But not without Prayer, and earneſtly contending for the Faith of Chriſt, touching any of his concernments; not a paſſionate contending is approved, but a zealous contending is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Lord, recorded by the Apoſtle; therefore hold faſt your zeal for God, little Remnant, who have given up your hearts and hands, and fore-heads to his Mark and Stamp, abhorring that of the beaſt, the Lord would have you let go paſſion, but love zeal, and hold it faſt, what ever men ſay of it, or do againſt you for it, yet let the zeal of the Lord eat you up, <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>The zeal of thy houſe hath eaten me up:</hi> Where are ſuch now? There are many that their pride and luſtfulneſſe, and vain-glory hath eaten them up, and ſwallowed what they ſeemed to hold forth, for others benefit, even for thoſe that are the Lords houſhold, but now ſelf hath devoured all, and the Lords heritage muſt wait for their Right, till their King Jeſus comes, whoſe right all power and Dominion is, and will take his great power and reign; who then ſhall gain-ſay him? Then there ſhall be no mockers, nor deriders to ſcoffe at the fifth Monarchy, where then ſhall be the table-ſcoffers, and the Pulpit-deriders, and ſuch that make a ſport and jeer at thoſe that are for Chriſts reign, and cry, Raze them; raze, even to the ground, their Perſons, Eſtates, and what ever is theirs; but the Lord laughs ſuch enemies to ſcorn, and hath them in deriſion, and will require and recover all from them that have defrauded; a fierce people ſhal not overcome the Lords Anointed, fierce looks, nor deep ſpeech gathered up and fetcht from both <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford</hi> Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhal not affright the Lords flock, though they ſtammer, they ſhal be underſtood, no dark ſaying ſhall be concealed from the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, they ſhall underſtand fierce looks, and deep ſubtile ſpeeches, though they be brought forth with a Latine tongue, and in Greek expreſſions, yet the wiſe-obſerving-ſpirited ones ſhall underſtand
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93777:35"/>the cunning works of the politick Sophiſter; glorious things ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the City of God: And the Lord incourageth the afflicted to hope and take confidence in him, who will bring judgement un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to victory; faithfull is he that hath promiſed, who will do it; then Saints may look upon Sion as the City of their ſolemnities, their eyes ſhall ſee <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a quiet habitation, a Tabernacle that ſhall not be taken down, not one of the ſtakes thereof ſhall ever be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, neither ſhall any of the cords thereof be broken, but there the glorious Lord will be unto us, a place of broad rivers, and ſtreams wherein ſhall go no gally with oars, neither ſhall gallant ſhip paſſe thereby: For the Lord is our Judge; the Lord is our Law-giver, the Lord is our King, he will ſave us, thy tackling are looſed, they could not well ſtrengthen their Maſt, they could not ſpread the Sail, then is the prey of a great ſpoil divided, the lame take the Prey, and the Inhabitants ſhall not ſay I am ſick: the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that dwell therein ſhall be forgiven their iniquity, this time is coming wherin the ſpoiler ſhal be ſpoiled, in the reſtauration of the Kingdom to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> then ſhall quietneſſe and peace that paſſeth all underſtanding be in their habitation, and round about them, no dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of men ſhall make them afraid, their Tabernacle no Politician ſhall take down, if any <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> or others ſhall ſtretch out their tongue or hand againſt the Lords Prophets, and Servants, they ſhall wither and ſhrink up with leproſie: For they that are true to the Lord, he wil be a Tabernacle unto them for a ſhadow in the day time from the heat, &amp; for a place of refuge, &amp; for a covert from ſtorm, and from rain, <hi>Iſa</hi> 4, 6. The Tabernacle ſpoken of in <hi>Leviticus,</hi> and in other places typed out Chriſt to come excellently, as the great Refuge and holy Center for his People, who bring their ſacrifices to him, they ſhall have admittance to enter in, being his Prieſts, they ſhall not ſtand at the door of the Tabernacle, but have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to come into this Tabernacle, and finde acceptance, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, what need they then matter whether men bid them welcome to their thrones and houſes or no, their welcome oftentimes is but a complement; for the moſt part not reall, but the Lords welcome and invitation is alwayes reall: Oh what ſtrong ſteaks and cords hath this Tabernacle, which is a ſtability of thoſe glorious times of Zion, none of her ſtrength or fortifications ſhall be broken or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken down by <hi>Bolial</hi> or any of his Crew: for their cords are not like thoſe green withs, which the Philiſtines brought to <hi>Dalilah</hi> to bind
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93777:35"/>
               <hi>Sampſon, Judg.</hi> 16. Chap. For the Lord hath made them abhor their Dalilah ſins, and cut off ſuch right hands, and pluck out ſuch right eyes, thoſe ſins that were ſo near and delightfull to them, they ſay, get you hence, they hate folly, and vain thoughts, and ſay with <hi>David</hi> in the 119. Pſalm, <hi>O how I love thy Law;</hi> unto ſuch will the glorious Lord be a place of broad rivers; not a narrow channel, nor a marſhy ditch, where the flags and ruſhes cover the water ſprings, nor a narrow winding Creek, where boats cannot paſſe along, neither is it ſhallow, but deep and broad, a place of broad rivers and ſtreams, its indeed an Ocean, it comprehends all rivers, and ſtreams, and this may be ſaid of it, Oh, the higth and depth, length and breadth; theſe are Rivers that the Waters riſe up to the Ancles, yea to the knees, and ſo to the loins, and at length they become a flowing high ſpring, that runs over banks,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezex.</hi> 47.3, 4, 5.</note> and fils the meadowes, and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> gives a report of theſe high ſpring Waters in his Propheſie, its good to be diptor plunged in this <hi>Jordan</hi> river, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> takes away all deformity, and cleanſeth from all leproſie, and its a comforting refreſhing River, this is Water of Life, it recovers the dying vitalls, and fainting Spirits, the which none of mens ſtrong li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors of Arts and Sciences can do, neither can any compounded water of humane invention be ſo effectuall, though they ſtill it in the Limbeck of brain-ſtudy, draining it through the long pipe of curious witty phraſes, yet ſuch Equors will ſoon loſe their ſpirits; but as for the Water that the ſoul drawes out of the Well of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, through Faiths Bucket, which retains the Sent and fragrant Smell, and operative Nature, and the ſoul ſwimes in the broad ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that are promiſed <hi>Zion;</hi> which Rivers will admit no gaily with oares to row therein, no troublers ſhall come there, none of mens gallantry, nor ſhips of Merchandiſe ſhall ſad there, no turkiſh, nor <hi>Engliſh</hi> gally of power and ſtrength and device, mannaged with Souldiour oares ſhall appear to take the free-born captive; that ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will preſently ſink ſuch gallies and oares too; and if ſo be gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Councel ſhips, and great numerous Parliament ſhips, which are made of wood; and pitch, and roſin, and tarre, and okum, ſuch ſtuff as wil burn to aſhes when the fire comes, which Scriptures ſpeaks of, its not the Clergy nails that can faſten ſuch ſhips toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make them ſail, which are heavy lumpiſh bottomes, that have no nimble ſwift motion at all, whereby to do ſervice for King
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:93777:36"/>Jeſus and his ſubjects: But the broad river is preparing, its making its path thorough all oppoſition, &amp; its ſhips are all making ready and preparing to ſwim: The great Ship-Wright, I ſpeak this with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and holy aw of God, and ſay that the great artificial Ship-Wright, and Carpenters Son ſo called by the Jews, which was the glorious Meſſiah, this mighty God is fitting his ſhips for this time, theſe are the <hi>Zion</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Micah</hi> 4.13. whoſe horns are Iron, and hoofs braſſe, who are exhorted to ariſe and threſh, and beat in pieces many people, and theſe will not waſte the gain, neither will they feaſt it away, but they will conſecrate it unto the Lord of the whole earth, they will ſerve his intereſt with it, not their own ends, and felfiſh intereſts.</p>
            <p>This is a time longed for by the New Non-conformiſts, who are Chriſts little flock, whom he bids not to fear, for it pleaſed his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to give them a Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Therefore get you to your ſtrong holds, Oh <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and Priſoners, for you are Priſoners of hope, you ſeek not great things for your ſelves, but for the Lords Anointed ones; you cry to the Lord, and not for earthly Palaces, nor <hi>White-Hall</hi>-Garden-Walkes, nor Kitchin-belly-chear, nor Lairdery-dainties, nor Banquet-ſweet-meats; nor Councell-Robes, nor Parliament Tithes nor Emperour Advancement, nor great Attendance, nor for Colonels and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains ſilken Buſſe, and garniſhed ſpangled Coats, and gilded Cloakes, and brave <hi>London</hi> and Country Houſes; I ſay, fellow-Priſoners and ſufferers for Chriſt, ſeeing we have none of this in our eye nor deſires, let us bid defiance to all reproaches, and vilify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and deriſions againſt us; this defiance have I preſented to <hi>Cornwall</hi> Clergie and Juſtices with their Auditories or Agents join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them, whether they be devout men or women, great gift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and learned, or ignorant; I bleſſe the Lord, I can ſend de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to all your reports, and reproachfull language there, and ſo I can to all ſuch here, and to their harſhneſſe, which ſay, it is pity but I ſhould be hanged, and that would commend a whip to my back; and to all baſe termes and names, and to <hi>Bridwell</hi> uſage too, I will write defiance, and ſay, Who can lay any thing to my charge, worthy of ſuch reproach, indictments, or binding over to the good behaviour, or of three or four priſons, or of ſending to <hi>Bridwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now in this defiance let all take their ſhare; Enemies take
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:93777:36"/>yours, and don't be offended at true ſpeaking, but be humbled and repent, that your evill words, and unjuſt actions, and thoughts of your heart may be forgiven you, and for you I ſhall pray.</p>
            <p>And to friends, I have this word, do not you find fault with op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, but labour to amend them with candid and charitable Conſtructions, and Spirituall Application of thoſe Scripture-Obſervations which are your due; and that we may all practiſe that which is good, and eſcape the evill, is the deſire and earneſt requeſt of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your praying Friend <hi>ANNA TRAPNELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:93777:37"/>
            <head>An Errata.</head>
            <p>IN page 17. line, 26. for horrible fit, read horrible pit. in page 19. line 15. for Haulbow, read Holſe. In page 24. line 9. read draw neer to the Table. page 27. line 13. for pin, read bring, and for through, read notwithſtanding their.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93777:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
